<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY GFDL SYSTEM "fdl-appendix.xml">
<!ENTITY app "Cheese">
<!ENTITY application "<application>&app;</application>">
<!ENTITY appversion "2.28">
<!ENTITY manrevision "2.28">
]>
<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Template Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project:
  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
-->
<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="ca">
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Manual del <application>Cheese</application></title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>
        <application>Cheese</application> uses your webcam to take photos and videos, applies
        fancy special effects and lets you share the fun with others.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2007-2009</year>
      <holder>daniel g. siegel (dgsiegel@gnome.org)</holder>
      <holder>Jaap A. Haitsma (jaap@haitsma.org)</holder>
      <holder>Filippo Argiolas (fargiolas@gnome.org)</holder>
    </copyright><copyright><year>2008, 2009</year><holder>Joan Duran (jodufi@gmail.com)</holder></copyright>

  <!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2006</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

  -->

<!-- An address can be added to the publisher information.  If a role is
     not specified, the publisher/author is the same for all versions of the
     document.  -->
    <publisher role="maintainer">
      <publishername>Felix Kaser (f.kaser@gmx.net)</publishername>
    </publisher>

     <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
	<para>Teniu permís per a copiar, distribuir i/o modificar aquest document, sota els termes de la Llicència de documentació lliure GNU (GFDL), versió 1.1 o qualsevol versió publicada posteriorment per la Free Software Foundation, sense seccions invariants, sense texts de portada i sense texts de contraportada. Podeu trobar una còpia de la GFDL en aquest <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:fdl">enllaç</ulink> o en el fitxer COPYING-DOCS distribuït amb aquest manual.</para>
         <para>Aquest manual forma part d'una col·lecció de manuals del GNOME distribuïts sota la GFDL. Si voleu distribuir aquest manual independentment de la col·lecció, podeu fer-ho afegint una còpia de la llicència al manual, tal com es descriu a la secció 6 de la llicència.</para>

	<para>Molts dels noms que les empreses utilitzen per a distingir els seus productes i serveis es consideren marques comercials. Quan aquests noms apareguin en qualsevol documentació del GNOME, si els membres del Projecte de documentació del GNOME han estat avisats pel que fa a les marques, els noms apareixeran en majúscules o amb les inicials en majúscules.</para>

	<para>EL DOCUMENT I LES VERSIONS MODIFICADES DEL DOCUMENT S'OFEREIXEN SOTA ELS TERMES DE LA LLICÈNCIA DE DOCUMENTACIÓ LLIURE DE GNU, TENINT EN COMPTE QUE: <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>EL DOCUMENT S'OFEREIX «TAL COM ÉS», SENSE CAP TIPUS DE GARANTIA, NI EXPLÍCITA NI IMPLÍCITA; AIXÒ INCLOU, SENSE LIMITAR-S'HI, LES GARANTIES QUE EL DOCUMENT O LA VERSIÓ MODIFICADA DEL DOCUMENT NO TINGUI DEFECTES, SIGUI COMERCIALITZABLE, SIGUI ADEQUAT PER A UN ÚS CONCRET O NO INFRINGEIXI CAP LLEI. TOT EL RISC PEL QUE FA A LA QUALITAT, EXACTITUD I RENDIMENT DEL DOCUMENT O LA VERSIÓ MODIFICADA DEL DOCUMENT ÉS VOSTRE. EN CAS QUE EL DOCUMENT RESULTÉS DEFECTUÓS EN QUALSEVOL ASPECTE, VÓS (NO PAS L'ESCRIPTOR INICIAL, L'AUTOR O CAP ALTRE COL·LABORADOR) ASSUMIU TOT EL COST DE MANTENIMENT, REPARACIÓ O CORRECCIÓ. AQUESTA RENÚNCIA DE GARANTIA CONSTITUEIX UNA PART ESSENCIAL D'AQUESTA LLICÈNCIA. NO S'AUTORITZA L'ÚS DE CAP DOCUMENT O VERSIÓ MODIFICADA DEL DOCUMENT EXCEPTE SOTA AQUESTA RENÚNCIA DE GARANTIA; I</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>EN CAP CAS I SOTA CAP INTERPRETACIÓ LEGAL, JA SIGUI PER AGREUJAMENT (INCLOENT-HI LA NEGLIGÈNCIA), CONTRACTE O ALTRE CAS, L'AUTOR, L'ESCRIPTOR ORIGINAL, QUALSEVOL DELS COL·LABORADORS O DISTRIBUÏDORS DEL DOCUMENT O UNA VERSIÓ MODIFICADA DEL DOCUMENT NI CAP PROVEÏDOR D'AQUESTES PARTS NO SERAN RESPONSABLES DAVANT DE NINGÚ PER CAP DANY DIRECTE, INDIRECTE, ESPECIAL, ACCIDENTAL O CONSECUTIU DE QUALSEVOL TIPUS; AIXÒ INCLOU, SENSE LIMITAR-S'HI, ELS DANYS PER PÈRDUA DE CLIENTS, INTERRUPCIONS DE LA FEINA, FALLADA O MALFUNCIONAMENT DE L'ORDINADOR, O QUALSEVOL ALTRA PÈRDUA O DANY RELACIONAT AMB L'ÚS DEL DOCUMENT I LES VERSIONS MODIFICADES DEL DOCUMENT, FINS I TOT SI S'HA INFORMAT AQUESTA PART DE LA POSSIBILITAT D'AQUESTS DANYS.</para>
		</listitem>
	  </orderedlist></para>
  </legalnotice>


   <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and
        other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change
        any of this. -->

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Joshua</firstname>
        <surname>Henderson</surname>
	<email>joshhendo@gmail.com</email>
      </author>
      <author>
        <firstname>Jaap</firstname>
        <surname>Haitsma</surname>
	<email>jaap@haitsma.org</email>
      </author>
      <author>
        <firstname>Felix</firstname>
        <surname>Kaser</surname>
	<email>f.kaser@gmx.net</email>
      </author>

<!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
      maintainers,  etc. Commented out by default.
       <othercredit role="translator">
        <firstname>Latin</firstname>
        <surname>Translator 1</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname>
          <address> <email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address>
        </affiliation>
        <contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
      </othercredit>
-->
    </authorgroup>

    <revhistory>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
        <date>04-12-2007</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para role="author">Jaap A. Haitsma <email>jaap@haitsma.org</email></para>
          <para role="publisher">Jaap A. Haitsma</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.2</revnumber>
        <date>12-01-2008</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para role="author">Jaap A. Haitsma <email>jaap@haitsma.org</email></para>
          <para role="author">Joshua Henderson <email>joshhendo@gmail.com</email></para>
          <para role="publisher">Jaap A. Haitsma</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.3</revnumber>
        <date>20-08-2008</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para role="author">Jaap A. Haitsma <email>jaap@haitsma.org</email></para>
          <para role="author">Joshua Henderson <email>joshhendo@gmail.com</email></para>
          <para role="publisher">Jaap A. Haitsma</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
      
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.4</revnumber>
        <date>2009-07-15</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para role="author">Jaap A. Haitsma <email>jaap@haitsma.org</email></para>
          <para role="author">Joshua Henderson <email>joshhendo@gmail.com</email></para>
          <para role="author">Felix Kaser
            <email>f.kaser@gmx.net</email>
          </para>
          <para role="publisher">Jaap A. Haitsma</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
			
			<revision>
        <revnumber>0.5</revnumber>
        <date>2009-09-14</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para role="author">Felix Kaser
            <email>f.kaser@gmx.net</email>
          </para>
          <para role="publisher">Felix Kaser</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>

    </revhistory>

    <legalnotice>
      <title>Comentaris</title>
      <para>
        To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding the Cheese application or
        this manual, follow the directions in the 
        <ulink url="http://projects.gnome.org/cheese/" type="http"><application>Cheese</application> project page</ulink>.
      </para>
<!-- Translators may also add here feedback address for translations -->
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <indexterm zone="index">
    <primary><application>Cheese</application></primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm zone="index">
    <primary>cheese</primary>
  </indexterm>

<!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->
<!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
<section id="intro">
  <title>Introducció</title>
  <!-- manrevision 2.0 compatibility -->
  <anchor id="aboutex"/>
  <anchor id="notice"/>
  <indexterm>
    <primary><application>Cheese</application></primary>
    <secondary>Manual</secondary>
    <tertiary>cheese</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
  Cheese uses your webcam to take photos and videos, applies
  fancy special effects and lets you share the fun with others.
  </para>

</section>

<section id="using">
  <title>Utilització</title>
  <para>
    The main screen of Cheese supports two different layouts at the moment.
		The default looks like the screenshot below, it has the preview image centered and
		the thumbnail slideshow below.
  </para>

  <figure>
  <title>Captura de pantalla del Cheese</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/cheese-main.jpg" format="JPG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
	
	<para>
		Especially for Cheese-users with small displays, like the ones in netbooks, we have designed
		another view. It is more horizontally aligned, in order to fit better on small widescreen displays.
		The wide-view is shown in the screenshot below.
	</para>
	
	<figure>
  <title>Cheese wide screenshot</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/cheese-wide.jpg" format="JPG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>
    Cheese uses the photo mode by defaults, but you can change this to use the video 
    or burst mode if desired.
  </para>

  <section id="using-effects">
    <title>Efectes</title>
    <para>
      To apply effects to the input of your webcam, click
      the button labelled <guibutton>Effects</guibutton>. When you then go to
      the effects window, you will see a window similar to the image below.
      <figure>
        <title>Captura de pantalla dels efectes del Cheese</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/cheese-effects.jpg" format="JPG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
       </screenshot>
      </figure>

    </para>

    <para>
      You can apply some really cool effects to your photos too! Just choose 
      from the several different effects available and click its corresponding
      button to apply it to your photo. Selecting multiple effects will apply 
      all the effects to your image. For example, if you select 
      <guibutton>Hulk</guibutton> and <guibutton>Vertical Flip</guibutton>, 
      the input from the webcam will be altered to have a green shade and be 
      upside down. To disable all effects, just click on the 
      <guibutton>No Effect</guibutton> button.
    </para>
		
		<para>
			To return to the preview of your webcam, just push the button 
            labelled <guibutton>Effects</guibutton> again. This will toggle 
            the Effects menu and bring you back to the normal view.
		</para>
  </section>

  <section id="using-photomode">
    <title>Mode de foto</title>
    <para>
      Photo mode is the default mode for Cheese. When not in photo mode,
      click the button that shows the icon of a single photo or select it from the menu:
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Cheese</guimenu><guimenuitem>Photo</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
      to change to photo mode.
      Photo mode will take a single photo every time the button labelled
      <guibutton>Take a photo</guibutton> or the <keycap>Spacebar</keycap>
      key is pressed, and will save to disk.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="using-videomode">
    <title>Mode de vídeo</title>
    <para>
      Video mode is a mode that allows you to take short videos using the webcam.
      When not in video mode, click the button that shows the icon of a film roll 
      or select it from the menu:
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Cheese</guimenu><guimenuitem>Video</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to
      change to video mode. Video mode will start recording a video every time 
      the button labelled <guibutton>Start Recording</guibutton> or the
      <keycap>Spacebar</keycap> is pressed. The video will stop
      recording and save to disk when the button labelled <guibutton>Stop
      Recording</guibutton> or the <keycap>Spacebar</keycap> is pressed.
    </para>

    <para>
      The video mode does not look much different from the photo mode,
      except that the button labelled <guibutton>Take a photo</guibutton> will
      say  <guibutton>Start Recording</guibutton> or <guibutton>Stop Recording</guibutton>,
      and the button with the film roll icon is pushed in, whereas the other 
      mode buttons (photo and burst) are not.
    </para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="using-burstmode">
    <title>Burst Mode</title>
    <para>
      In burst mode you can take more pictures in a row. It works exactly like 
      the photo mode, except that it takes a series of pictures. When you are 
      not in burst mode, click the button that shows the icon of several 
      pictures in a row or select it from the menu: <menuchoice><guimenu>Cheese</guimenu><guimenuitem>Burst</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to
      change to burst mode. Burst mode will start to take a series of 
      pictures with an interval of some seconds in between photos when the 
      button labelled <guibutton>Take Multiple Photos</guibutton> or the 
      <keycap>Spacebar</keycap> key is pressed.
      The delay and amount of pictures to take can be set in the preferences 
      dialog. For more information please see <xref linkend="preferences"/>.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        All modes can be used in fullscreen. To do this, click the 
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Cheese</guimenu><guimenuitem>Fullscreen</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu to
        enter fullscreen mode, or press the <keycap>F11</keycap> key. To exit fullscreen
        mode, press the <keycap>Esc</keycap> or the <keycap>F11</keycap> keys.
      </para>
    </note>
		
		<figure>
    <title>Cheese fullscreen screenshot</title>
    	<screenshot>
      	<mediaobject>
        	<imageobject>
          	<imagedata fileref="figures/cheese-fullscreen.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
     	</screenshot>
    </figure>
	</section>
  
</section>

<section id="working-with">
  <title>Com treballar amb fotos i vídeos</title>
  <section id="takingaphoto">
    <title>Com fer una foto</title>
    <para>
      To take a photo with Cheese, be sure to be in the “Photo” mode.
    </para>

    <para>
      It's easy to take photos with special effects. Just click the button
      labelled <guibutton>Effects</guibutton>, and click on the effects desired as
      described in <xref linkend="using-effects"/>. You should now have the effects that
      you chose applied to the webcam input. Press the effects button again to 
      get back to the normal view.
    </para>

    <para>
      To take a photo, press the button labelled <guibutton>Take a photo</guibutton>
      or press the <keycap>spacebar</keycap> key. Alternatively, you can also use 
      the webcam capture button, if your webcam has one. You will then
      see <application>Cheese</application> count down from 3 or instantly take the photo, 
      depending on your settings. When the photo is taken, your entire screen
      will flash white, and the photo that was just taken will appear in the photo
      stream at the bottom of the program's window. To abort the countdown you can use the
      <keycap>Esc</keycap> key.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="recordingavideo">
    <title>Recording a video</title>
    <para>
      To record a video in Cheese, make sure that the <guibutton>Video</guibutton>
      button has been pressed.
    </para>

    <para>
      To start recording a video, press the button labelled <guibutton>Start
      Recording</guibutton> or press the <keycap>Spacebar</keycap> key. Alternatively,
      you can also use the webcam capture button, if your webcam has one.
      To stop recording just press the same button, now labelled <guibutton>Stop
      Recording</guibutton>, and the recording will stop and the video saved.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        If your video appears to be jerky or has a low
        frame rate (only updating the picture every few seconds), it does not mean that the recording
        has a similar frame rate. In many cases, the recorded file will have a better frame rate.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
	
	<section id="takingburst">
    <title>Taking a series of pictures in burst mode</title>
    <para>
      To take more than one picture over some time you can use the burst mode.
			Burst mode can be set up in the preferences dialog where you can also set the
			amount of pictures you want to take and the delay in seconds between them.
			You can find more information about that in <xref linkend="preferences"/>.
    </para>

    <para>
      To start the burst mode, press the button labelled <guibutton>Take Multiple Photos</guibutton>
			or press the <keycap>Spacebar</keycap> key. Alternatively, you can also use the webcam capture button,
			if your webcam has one. To stop the burst capture you can use the
			<keycap>Esc</keycap> key.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

<section id="setting-up">
  <title>Setting up Cheese</title>
	
	<section id="preferences">
    <title>The preferences dialog</title>
    <para>
      The preferences dialog allows you to set up some webcam specific parameters and
			parameters specific to the burst mode. If you have more than one webcam or video device attached
			to your system, the preferences dialog allows you to choose which one you would like to use for Cheese and
			what resolution the image should have. Use the sliders to play around with the
			brightness, contrast, saturation and hue values to find the best for your webcam.
    </para>
		
		<figure>
			<title>Cheese preferences screenshot</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/cheese-preferences.jpg" format="JPG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
		</figure>

    <para>
      The parameters for the burst mode can be set in the preferences dialog as well. You only
			have to adjust the values for the number of photos you wish to take and the delay 
            in seconds between each picture taken.
    </para>
  </section>
	
	<section id="gconf">
		<title>GConf settings</title>
		<para>
			It's possible to define where Cheese stores the captured media (photos and videos). These
			settings are stored in GConf. You can change the settings with the <command>gconf-editor</command>,
			application. There you have to select /apps/cheese in the tree on the left. Then you can set the <guilabel>video_path</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>photo_path</guilabel> to the location you prefer. There you can also set other parameters
			for Cheese, but you should use the preferences dialog for a controlled access.
    </para>
		
		<warning>
      <para>Attention: Be careful while using GConf to change your settings! If you are not completely sure about what
			you are doing, you should ask someone who knows!</para>
    </warning>
	</section>
</section>

<section id="sharing">
  <title>Compartició de fotos i vídeos</title>

  <section id="view">
    <title>Com visualitzar una foto o un vídeo</title>
    <para>
      To view a video or photo that has been taken, locate it in the photo stream and
      double click it. Alternatively, you can right click on it and select <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>.
      This will then open the file in the default application for that file type.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="saving">
    <title>Com desar fotos i vídeos en una ubicació alternativa</title>
    <para>
      To save a photo to an alternate place on your system where you can easily
      find them, find the photo or video that you wish to save in the photo stream, right
      click on it and select <guimenuitem>Save As</guimenuitem> from the pop-up menu. This will bring up a
      standard <guilabel>Save File</guilabel> dialog that will allow you to save it to a new location
      as well as rename it if you so wish to do.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="delete">
    <title>Com suprimir una foto</title>
    <para>
      To delete a photo from the photo stream, locate the photo you wish to delete in
      the photo stream, left click on it once and press the <keycap>delete</keycap> button on your
      keyboard. Alternatively, you can right click on it and select <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>
      from the pop-up menu.
    </para>

    <para>
      You will be asked if you wish to delete it from the photo stream. To confirm,
      press the button labelled <guibutton>Move to Trash</guibutton>.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        This will move the image to the "trash", as well as remove from
        your photo stream. This will not remove the photo from your computer. To remove
        it from your system, you will need to empty your trash.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="email">
    <title>Com enviar una foto per correu electrònic</title>
    <para>
      Photos can be directly emailed from Cheese. You will need to have the default mail
      client set up with an email account. To email
      a photo, locate the photo in the photo stream, right click on
      it and select <guimenuitem>Send by Mail</guimenuitem>.
    </para>

    <para>
      This will open the default mail client (for example, Evolution) and a new email
      message will be created with the photo you selected as an attachment.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="account-photo">
    <title>Com establir una foto com a foto del compte</title>
    <para>
      To set a photo as your account photo (which can be viewed from the 
      <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
      <guimenuitem>About Me</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu, and the login window with a list of
      user names with photos), locate the photo that you wish to use in Cheese, right click
      on it and select <guimenuitem>Set as Account Photo</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="fspot">
    <title>Com exportar una foto a l'F-Spot</title>
    <para>
      To export a photo to F-Sport, locate the photo in your photo
      stream, right click on it and select <guimenuitem>Export to F-Spot</guimenuitem>. You will then be prompted by
      F-Spot if you wish to import the photos that are being sent to it.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>Depenent de la versió del Cheese que esteu utilitzant actualment, l'F-Spot us preguntarà si voleu importar tot el flux de fotos.</para>
    </note>
	
	<figure>
		<title>Cheese sharing screenshot</title>
		<screenshot>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="figures/cheese-share.jpg" format="JPG"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
	 </screenshot>
	</figure>
  </section>
</section>

<!--<section id="preferences">
  <title>Preferences</title>

  <para>
    Describe preferences over here
  </para>
</section>-->

<section id="faq">
  <title>Preguntes més freqüents</title>
  <!--<para>
    These are questions the mailing list gets asked frequently.
  </para>-->

  <section id="faq-sluggish">
    <title>El vídeo té una resposta lenta. Què puc fer?</title>
    <para>
      You may have set "<literal>ximagesink</literal>" (<guilabel>X Window System (No Xv)</guilabel>) as video-output.
      This means that your CPU is doing all the work. Change it to "<literal>xvimagesink</literal>"
      (<guilabel>X Window System (X11/XShm/Xv)</guilabel>) in order to let your graphics card do the work.
    </para>

    <para>
      To change this setting, run the <command>gstreamer-properties</command>
      command, click the <guilabel>Video</guilabel> tab
      and change the appropriate setting.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="faq-mac">
    <title>Tinc un Mac amb iSight i una targeta gràfica ATI, i els colors són estranys.</title>
    <para>Aquest és un problema amb les targetes gràfiques ATI, encara que hi ha una alternativa. Canvieu la sortida de vídeo a personalitzada i inseriu el següent: «<literal>ffmpegcolorspace ! video/x-raw-yuv,format=(fourcc)YV12 ! ffmpegcolorspace ! xvimagesink</literal>».</para>

    <para>
      To change this setting, run the <command>gstreamer-properties</command> command, 
      click the <guilabel>Video</guilabel> tab
      and select custom from the drop down menu.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="faq-work-gstreamer">
    <title>La meva càmera web funciona amb el GStreamer, però no funciona amb el <application>Cheese</application>. Quin és el problema?</title>
    <para>
      Using the <command>gstreamer-properties</command> mentioned in the above question, try changing from
      <guilabel>xvimagesink</guilabel> to <guilabel>ximagesink</guilabel> or vice-versa.
      If this still does not work, run <command>cheese --verbose</command> on
      the command line and copy the logging into a bug report in our 
      <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=cheese" type="http">
      bug tracker</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="faq-work-other">
    <title>La meva càmera web funciona amb altres programes com ara l'Ekiga, el Camorama, però no amb el <application>Cheese</application>. Quin és el problema?</title>
    <para>Vegeu si la càmera web funciona comprovant-la amb el <command>gstreamer-properties</command>. Si funciona aquí, però no al <application>Cheese</application>, introduïu un informe d'error al nostre <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=cheese" type="http">seguidor d'errors</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="faq-store">
    <title>Where does <application>Cheese</application> store my photos and videos?</title>
    <para>
      Cheese stores your pictures in a folder called Webcam inside the
      XDG-Directory set for Pictures (in most distributions its ~/Pictures/Webcam).
      The same applies for Videos: ~/Videos/Webcam. XDG is a standard to
      declare default folders in your system. You can find more information
      about XDG <ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/basedir-spec/basedir-spec-0.6.html" type="http">here</ulink>.
    </para>  

    <para>
      If the XDG-Path is not set on your System, cheese has a fallback solution: it
      will store both your pictures and videos in ~/.gnome2/cheese/media. This is the default
      directory for your media if you have an older version of <application>Cheese</application>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      How to set an alternate path is described in <xref linkend="gconf"/>.
    </para>
    
    <warning>
      <para>Attention: leave this settings blank if you want <application>Cheese</application> to use the default directories.</para>
    </warning>
    
    <note>
		  <para>
		    You can also save your pictures to an alternate location from within Cheese. Please see
		    <xref linkend="saving"/> for information on this.
		  </para>
		</note>
  </section>

  <section id="faq-quickcam">
    <title>La meva Quickcam Express no funciona amb el <application>Cheese</application>...</title>
    <para>o el GStreamer, i veig errors com ara «No hi ha suficients conductes. Se n'ha obtingut 1, se'n necessiten com a mínim 2» a la sortida del <application>Cheese</application>. Amb el controlador «qc-usb».</para>

    <para>Per a habilitar el mode de compatibilitat amb dos conductes, intenteu executar <command>qcset /dev/video0 compat=dblbuf</command>, llavors reinicieu el <application>Cheese</application>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="faq-no-camera-found">
    <title>Missatge d'error «No s'ha trobat cap càmera»</title>
    <para>
      "When I launch Cheese, I get the message 'No Camera Found' but I have my webcam plugged into my computer".

      There are many situations that can cause this, and the exact problem that is causing it needs to be isolated.
      If possible, try each of the following to try and get your webcam working:
        1. Plug your webcam into another computer. If it works there, then it is a problem 
           with the connection to your computer, or the operating system if it was a different
           one on the other computer. Check the ports on your computer (try another one) and
           consult support for your particular operating system.
        2. See if your camera is being detected by your computer. On Linux, open up the terminal or console and type
           "dmesg" before you plug in your webcam. Notice the most recent entries, and then plug in your webcam. Type
           "dmesg" again and see if the most recent entries differ. If the message mentions a USB device being detected,
           and your webcam is the only USB device that has been changed, then your computer is detecting your webcam
           fine. If not, then test to see if the webcam is working on another computer. This may only work with USB
           webcams.
        3. As Cheese uses the gstreamer backend, it is most likely because gstreamer is not detecting the webcam (or
           gstreamer has become corrupt). Please contact support for the particular operating system that
           you are running with as many details as possible. For Ubuntu, please use the <ulink url="http://ubuntuforums.org/" type="http">Ubuntu Forums</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="faq-supported-webcams">
    <title>Which cameras are supported?</title>
    <para>
      Cheese uses gstreamer for video grabbing. So in principle Cheese supports 
      any camera that works with GStreamer. That should be any camera
      which supports video4linux or video4linux2.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

<section id="about">
  <title>Quant a</title>
  <para>
    Cheese was initially written by Daniel G. Siegel <email>dgsiegel@gnome.org</email>.
    as a Google Summer of Code project. Later, Jaap A. Haitsma <email>jaap@haitsma.org</email> and 
    others joined Daniel to improve it.
    To find more information about Cheese, please visit the
    <ulink url="http://projects.gnome.org/cheese" type="http">
    <application>Cheese</application> web page</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
    To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this application, you can file
    a bug in our 
    <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=cheese" type="http">
    bug tracker</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>Aquest programa es distribueix sota els termes de la Llicència pública general de GNU tal com publica la Free Software Foundation; tant en la versió 2 de la llicència, o (a la vostra opció) una versió posterior. Es pot trobar una còpia d'aquesta llicència al <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html" type="http">lloc web del GNU</ulink>, o en el fitxer COPYING inclòs amb el codi font d'aquest programa.</para>
</section>

</article>
