<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % DISTRO_SPECIFICS SYSTEM "distro-specifics.ent">
<!ENTITY DISTRO_MAINMENU '<guimenu>the main menu on the panel (the menu with the "f" icon)</guimenu>'>
<!ENTITY % SYSTEM_CONFIG_NFS_DISTRO_SPECIFICS SYSTEM "system-config-nfs-distro-specifics.ent">
<!ENTITY SYSTEM_CONFIG_NFS_TOOL "NFS Server Configuration Tool">
<!ENTITY SYSTEM_CONFIG_NFS_INVOCATION '
    <indexterm significance="normal">
        <primary><command>system-config-nfs</command>
        </primary>
        <see>&SYSTEM_CONFIG_NFS_TOOL;</see>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
        You must be running the <application>X</application> Window System and have root privileges to use the &SYSTEM_CONFIG_NFS_TOOL;. To start the application on the desktop, go to <menuchoice>&DISTRO_MAINMENU;<guisubmenu>System</guisubmenu><guisubmenu>Administration</guisubmenu><guisubmenu>Server Settings</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>NFS</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
    </para>
'>
<!ENTITY SYSTEM_CONFIG_NFS_ABSTRACT SYSTEM "system-config-nfs-abstract.xml">
<!ENTITY SYSTEM_CONFIG_NFS_CONTENT SYSTEM "system-config-nfs-content.xml">
<!ENTITY SYSTEM_CONFIG_NFS_HOSTNAME_FORMATS SYSTEM "system-config-nfs-hostname-formats.xml">
]>
<article lang="pa"><title>NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ</title><articleinfo><revhistory><revision><revnumber>1.0</revnumber><date>2008-01-17</date></revision><revision><revnumber>1.0.1</revnumber><date>2008-03-12</date></revision></revhistory><abstract role="description"><para>ਨੈੱਟਵਰਕ ਫਾਇਲ ਸਿਸਟਮ (NFS) ਨੈੱਟਵਰਕ ਉੱਪਰ ਮਸ਼ੀਨਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਸਾਂਝੀਆਂ ਕਰਨ ਦਾ ਇੱਕ ਤਰੀਕਾ ਹੈ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਕਲਾਂਈਟ ਦੀ ਲੋਕਲ ਹਾਰਡ ਡਿਸਕ ਤੇ ਪਈਆਂ ਹਨ। ਤੁਹਾਡੀ ਮਸ਼ੀਨ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਅਤੇ ਇੱਕ NFS ਕਲਾਂਈਟ ਦੋਨੋਂ ਹੀ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਦਾ ਮਤਲਬ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਇਹ ਦੂਜੇ ਸਿਸਟਮਾਂ ਤੇ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਨਿਰਯਾਤ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਮਾਊਂਟ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ ਜੇ ਫਾਇਲ ਹੋਰ ਮਸ਼ੀਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਨਿਰਯਾਤ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ ਹੋਣ।</para><para>ਇੱਕ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਤੋਂ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਸਾਂਝੀਆਂ ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟਰੀ ਪੱਧਰ ਤੇ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ ਜਾਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ਜਿਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਹਨ, ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟਰੀ ਦਾ "ਨਿਰਯਾਤ" ਕਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ। <application>NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਸੰਦ</application> ਨੂੰ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਵਰਤਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ।</para>
</abstract><authorgroup><corpauthor role="maintainer"><trademark class="registered">Red Hat</trademark>, Inc.</corpauthor></authorgroup></articleinfo>    <para>ਨੈੱਟਵਰਕ ਫਾਇਲ ਸਿਸਟਮ (NFS) ਨੈੱਟਵਰਕ ਉੱਪਰ ਮਸ਼ੀਨਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਸਾਂਝੀਆਂ ਕਰਨ ਦਾ ਇੱਕ ਤਰੀਕਾ ਹੈ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਕਲਾਂਈਟ ਦੀ ਲੋਕਲ ਹਾਰਡ ਡਿਸਕ ਤੇ ਪਈਆਂ ਹਨ। ਤੁਹਾਡੀ ਮਸ਼ੀਨ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਅਤੇ ਇੱਕ NFS ਕਲਾਂਈਟ ਦੋਨੋਂ ਹੀ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਦਾ ਮਤਲਬ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਇਹ ਦੂਜੇ ਸਿਸਟਮਾਂ ਤੇ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਨਿਰਯਾਤ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਮਾਊਂਟ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ ਜੇ ਫਾਇਲ ਹੋਰ ਮਸ਼ੀਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਨਿਰਯਾਤ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ ਹੋਣ।</para><para>ਇੱਕ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਤੋਂ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਸਾਂਝੀਆਂ ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟਰੀ ਪੱਧਰ ਤੇ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ ਜਾਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ਜਿਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਫਾਇਲਾਂ ਹਨ, ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟਰੀ ਦਾ "ਨਿਰਯਾਤ" ਕਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ। <application>NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਸੰਦ</application> ਨੂੰ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਵਰਤਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ।</para>


    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary><command>system-config-nfs</command>
        </primary><see>NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਸੰਦ</see></indexterm><para>ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ <application>X</application> ਵਿੰਡੋ ਸਿਸਟਮ ਚਲਾਉਣਾ ਪਵੇਗਾ ਅਤੇ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਸੰਦ ਵਰਤਣ ਲਈ ਪਰਬੰਧਕ ਅਧਿਕਾਰ ਹੋਣੇ ਜਰੂਰੀ ਹਨ। ਡੈਸਕਟਾਪ ਤੇ ਐਪਲੀਕੇਸ਼ਨਾਂ ਚਲਾਉਣ ਲਈ, <menuchoice><guimenu>ਪੈਨਲ ਦਾ ਮੁੱਖ ਮੇਨੂ ("f" ਆਈਕਾਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਮੇਨੂ)</guimenu><guisubmenu>ਸਿਸਟਮ</guisubmenu><guisubmenu>ਪਰਸ਼ਾਸ਼ਨ</guisubmenu><guisubmenu>ਸਰਵਰ ਸੈਟਿੰਗ</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>NFS</guimenuitem></menuchoice> ਤੇ ਜਾਓ।</para>

	
	<figure float="0" id="fig-system-config-nfs"><title><application>NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਸੰਦ</application></title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/system-config-nfs.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject><textobject><para>NFS ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਸੰਦ</para></textobject></mediaobject></figure>

	<para>ਕੁਝ ਫਾਇਰਵਾਲ ਸੈਟਿੰਗਾਂ ਦੇ ਅਧਾਰ ਤੇ, ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ NFS ਡੈਮਨ ਕਾਰਜ ਸੰਰਚਿਤ ਕਰਨੇ ਪੈਣਗੇ ਤਾਂ ਜੋ ਖਾਸ ਨੈੱਟਵਰਕ ਪੋਰਟਾਂ ਵਰਤੀਆਂ ਜਾ ਸਕਣ। NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੈਟਿੰਗ ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ ਹਰੇਕ ਕਾਰਜ ਲਈ ਪੋਰਟ ਨਿਰਧਾਰਤ ਕਰਨੀ ਪਵੇਗੀ ਨਾਂ ਕਿ ਪੋਰਟਮੈਪਰ ਦੁਆਰਾ ਨਿਰਧਾਰਤ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ ਲਗਾਤਾਰ ਪੋਰਟਾਂ। ਤੁਸੀਂ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੈਟਿੰਗ <guibutton>ਸਰਵਰ ਸੈਟਿੰਗ</guibutton> ਬਟਨ ਦਬਾ ਕੇ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ ਹੋ। ਹੇਠਲੀ ਤਸਵੀਰ NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੈਟਿੰਗ ਵਿੰਡੋ ਵੇਖਾਉਂਦੀ ਹੈ।</para>
	<figure float="0" id="fig-nfs-server-settings"><title><application>NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੈਟਿੰਗ</application></title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/system-config-nfs-server-settings.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject><textobject><para>NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੈਟਿੰਗ</para></textobject></mediaobject></figure>
	<section id="s2-nfs-export"><title>NFS ਫਾਇਲ ਸਿਸਟਮ ਨਿਰਯਾਤ ਜਾਂ ਸਾਂਝ</title><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>NFS</primary><secondary>ਨਿਰਯਾਤ</secondary></indexterm><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>NFS ਫਾਇਲ ਸਿਸਟਮ </primary></indexterm><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>ਫਾਇਲ ਸਿਸਟਮ</primary><secondary>NFS</secondary><see>NFS</see></indexterm><indexterm significance="normal"><primary><application>NFS ਸਰਵਰ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਸੰਦ</application></primary></indexterm><para>Sharing or serving files from an NFS server is known as "exporting" the directories which contain the files. The <application>NFS Server Configuration Tool</application> can be used to configure a system as an NFS server.</para><para>ਇੱਕ NFS ਸਾਂਝ ਸ਼ਾਮਿਲ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ, <guibutton>ਸ਼ਾਮਿਲ</guibutton> ਬਟਨ ਦਬਾਓ। <xref linkend="fig-add-share"/> ਵਿੱਚ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਡਾਇਲਾਗ ਬਾਕਸ ਦਿਸਦਾ ਹੈ।</para><para><guilabel>ਮੁੱਢਲਾ</guilabel> ਟੈਬ ਲਈ ਹੇਠਲੀ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਚਾਹੀਦੀ ਹੈ:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟਰੀ</guilabel> — ਸਾਂਝ ਲਈ ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟਰੀ ਦੱਸਦੀ ਹੈ, ਜਿਵੇਂ <filename>/tmp</filename>।</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Host(s)</guilabel> — Specify the host(s) with which to share the directory. Refer to <xref linkend="s2-nfs-hostname-formats"/> for an explanation of possible formats.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>ਮੁੱਢਲੇ ਅਧਿਕਾਰ</guilabel> — ਦੱਸਦੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟਰੀ ਤੇ ਸਿਰਫ-ਪੜਨ ਜਾਂ ਪੜਨ/ਲਿਖਣ ਦੇ ਅਧਿਕਾਰ ਹਨ।</para></listitem></itemizedlist><figure float="0" id="fig-add-share"><title>ਸਾਂਝ ਸ਼ਾਮਿਲ</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/system-config-nfs-add-basic.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject><textobject><para>NFS ਸ਼ੇਅਰ ਸ਼ਾਮਿਲ</para></textobject></mediaobject></figure><para><guilabel>ਆਮ ਚੋਣਾਂ</guilabel> ਟੈਬ ਹੇਠਲੀਆਂ ਚੋਣਾਂ ਸੰਰਚਿਤ ਕਰਨ ਦਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ:</para><figure float="0" id="fig-nfs-general-options"><title>NFS ਆਮ ਚੋਣਾਂ</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/system-config-nfs-add-general-options.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject><textobject><para>ਆਮ ਚੋਣਾਂ</para></textobject></mediaobject></figure><itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Allow connections from port 1024 and higher</guilabel> — Services started on port numbers less than 1024 must be started as root. Select this option to allow the NFS service to be started by a user other than root. This option corresponds to <command>insecure</command>.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Allow insecure file locking</guilabel> — Do not require a lock request. This option corresponds to <command>insecure_locks</command>.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Disable subtree checking</guilabel> — If a subdirectory of a file system is exported, but the entire file system is not exported, the server checks to see if the requested file is in the subdirectory exported. This check is called <firstterm>subtree checking</firstterm>. Select this option to disable subtree checking. If the entire file system is exported, selecting to disable subtree checking can increase the transfer rate. This option corresponds to <command>no_subtree_check</command>.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Sync write operations on request</guilabel> — Enabled by default, this option does not allow the server to reply to requests before the changes made by the request are written to the disk. This option corresponds to <command>sync</command>. If this is not selected, the <command>async</command> option is used.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Force sync of write operations immediately</guilabel> — Do not delay writing to disk. This option corresponds to <command>no_wdelay</command>.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Hide filesystems beneath</guilabel> turns the <command>nohide</command> option on or off. When the <command>nohide</command> option is off, nested directories are revealed. The clients can therefore navigate through a filesystem from the parent without noticing any changes.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Export only if mounted</guilabel> sets the <command>mountpoint</command> option which allows a directory to be exported only if it has been mounted.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Optional Mount Point</guilabel> specifies the path to an optional mount point. Click on the <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> to navigate to the preferred mount point or type the path if known.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Set explicit Filesystem ID:</guilabel> sets the <command>fsid=X</command> option. This is mainly used in a clustered setup. Using a consistent filesystem ID in all clusters avoids having stale NFS filehandles.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><figure float="0" id="fig-nfs-user-access"><title>NFS ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਪਹੁੰਚ</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/system-config-nfs-add-user-access.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject><textobject><para>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਪਹੁੰਚ</para></textobject></mediaobject></figure><para><guilabel>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਪਹੁੰਚ</guilabel> ਟੈਬ ਹੇਠਲੀਆਂ ਚੋਣਾਂ ਸੰਰਚਿਤ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਮਨਜੂਰੀ ਦਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Treat remote root user as local root</guilabel> — By default, the user and group IDs of the root user are both 0. Root squashing maps the user ID 0 and the group ID 0 to the user and group IDs of anonymous so that root on the client does not have root privileges on the NFS server. If this option is selected, root is not mapped to anonymous, and root on a client has root privileges to exported directories. Selecting this option can greatly decrease the security of the system. Do not select it unless it is absolutely necessary. This option corresponds to <command>no_root_squash</command>.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Treat all client users as anonymous users</guilabel> — If this option is selected, all user and group IDs are mapped to the anonymous user. This option corresponds to <command>all_squash</command>.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Specify local user ID for anonymous users</guilabel> — If <guilabel>Treat all client users as anonymous users</guilabel> is selected, this option lets you specify a user ID for the anonymous user. This option corresponds to <command>anonuid</command>.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Specify local group ID for anonymous users</guilabel> — If <guilabel>Treat all client users as anonymous users</guilabel> is selected, this option lets you specify a group ID for the anonymous user. This option corresponds to <command>anongid</command>.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem></itemizedlist><para>To edit an existing NFS share, select the share from the list, and click the <guibutton>Properties</guibutton> button. To delete an existing NFS share, select the share from the list, and click the <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button.</para><indexterm significance="normal"><primary><filename>/etc/exports</filename></primary></indexterm><indexterm significance="normal"><primary><filename>exports</filename></primary></indexterm><para>After clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to add, edit, or delete an NFS share from the list, the changes take place immediately — the server daemon is restarted and the old configuration file is saved as <filename>/etc/exports.bak</filename>. The new configuration is written to <filename>/etc/exports</filename>.</para><para>The <application>NFS Server Configuration Tool</application> reads and writes directly to the <filename>/etc/exports</filename> configuration file. Thus, the file can be modified manually after using the tool, and the tool can be used after modifying the file manually (provided the file was modified with correct syntax).</para></section>
<appendix><title>ਸੂਚੀ</title><section id="s2-nfs-hostname-formats"><title>ਮੇਜ਼ਬਾਨ-ਨਾਂ ਫਾਰਮੈਟ</title><indexterm significance="normal"><primary>NFS</primary><secondary>ਮੇਜ਼ਬਾਨ-ਨਾਂ ਫਾਰਮੈਟ</secondary></indexterm><para>ਮੇਜ਼ਬਾਨ ਹੇਠਲੇ ਰੂਪ ਵਿੱਚ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੇ ਹਨ:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Single machine — A fully qualified domain name (that can be resolved by the server), hostname (that can be resolved by the server), or an IP address.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Series of machines specified with wildcards — Use the * or ? character to specify a string match. Wildcards are not to be used with IP addresses; however, they may accidentally work if reverse DNS lookups fail. When specifying wildcards in fully qualified domain names, dots (.) are not included in the wildcard. For example, <computeroutput>*.example.com</computeroutput> includes one.example.com but does not include one.two.example.com.</para></listitem><listitem><para>IP ਨੈੱਟਵਰਕ — <replaceable>a.b.c.d/z</replaceable> ਵਰਤੋਂ, ਜਿੱਥੇ <replaceable>a.b.c.d</replaceable> ਨੈੱਟਵਰਕ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ <replaceable>z</replaceable> ਨੈੱਟਮਾਸਕ ਦੀਆਂ ਬਿੱਟਾਂ ਦੀ ਗਿਣਤੀ ਹੈ (ਉਦਾਹਰਨ ਲਈ 192.168.0.0/24)। ਹੋਰ ਫਾਰਮੈਟ ਹੈ <replaceable>a.b.c.d/netmask</replaceable>, ਜਿੱਥੇ <replaceable>a.b.c.d</replaceable> ਨੈੱਟਵਰਕ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ <replaceable>netmask</replaceable> ਨੈੱਟਮਾਸਕ ਹੈ (ਉਦਾਹਰਨ ਲਈ, 192.168.100.8/255.255.255.0).</para></listitem><listitem><para>ਨੈੱਟ-ਗਰੁੱਪ — <replaceable>@group-name</replaceable> ਫਾਰਮੈਟ ਵਿੱਚ, ਜਿੱਥੇ <replaceable>group-name</replaceable> NIS ਨੈੱਟ-ਗਰੁੱਪ ਨਾਂ ਹੈ।</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section>
</appendix></article>
