<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "About_Fedora.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<article lang="en-US">
	<xi:include href="Article_Info.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"></xi:include>
	<para>
		Fedora is an open, innovative, forward looking operating system and platform, based on Linux, that is always free for anyone to use, modify and distribute, now and forever. It is developed by a large community of people who strive to provide and maintain the very best in free, open source software and standards. Fedora is part of the Fedora Project, sponsored by Red Hat, Inc.
	</para>
	<para>
		Visit the Fedora community Wiki at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/"></ulink>.
	</para>
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Fedora_Documentation">
		<title>Fedora Documentation</title>
		<para>
			The Fedora Documentation Project provides 100% Free/Libre Open Source Software (FLOSS) content, services, and tools for documentation. We welcome volunteers and contributors of all skill levels. Visit our Web page at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/DocsProject"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Fedora_Translation">
		<title>Fedora Translation</title>
		<para>
			The goal of the Translation Project is to translate the software and the documentation associated with the Fedora Project. Visit our Web page at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Translation"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Fedora_Bug_Squad">
		<title>Fedora Bug Squad</title>
		<para>
			The primary mission of the Fedora Bug Squad is to track down and clear bugs in <ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/bugzilla">Bugzilla</ulink> that are related to Fedora, and act as a bridge between users and developers. Visit our Web page at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/BugZappers"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Fedora_Marketing">
		<title>Fedora Marketing</title>
		<para>
			The Fedora Marketing Project is the Fedora Project&#39;s public voice. Our goal is to promote Fedora and to help promote other Linux and open source projects. Visit our Web page at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Marketing"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Fedora_Ambassadors">
		<title>Fedora Ambassadors</title>
		<para>
			Fedora Ambassadors are people who go to places where other Linux users and potential converts gather and tell them about Fedora &mdash; the project and the distribution. Visit our Web page at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Ambassadors"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Fedora_Infrastructure">
		<title>Fedora Infrastructure</title>
		<para>
			The Fedora Infrastructure Project is about helping all Fedora contributors get their work done with minimum hassle and maximum efficiency. Information technology this umbrella include the build system, the <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Infrastructure/AccountSystem">Fedora Account System</ulink>, the <ulink url="http://cvs.fedoraproject.org/">CVS repositories</ulink>, the <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Communicate">mailing lists</ulink>, and the <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Websites">Websites</ulink> infrastructure. Visit our Web site at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Infrastructure"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Fedora_Websites">
		<title>Fedora Websites</title>
		<para>
			The Fedora Websites initiative aims to improve Fedora&#39;s image on the Internet. The key goals of this effort include:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Trying to consolidate all the key Fedora websites onto one uniform scheme
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Maintaining the content that doesn&#39;t fall under any particular sub-project
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Generally, making the sites as fun and exciting as the project they represent!
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Visit our Web page at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Websites"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Fedora_Artwork">
		<title>Fedora Artwork</title>
		<para>
			Making things look pretty is the name of the game. Icons, desktop backgrounds, and themes are all parts of the Fedora Artwork Project. Visit our Web page at <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Artwork"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-About_Fedora-Planet_Fedora">
		<title>Planet Fedora</title>
		<para>
			You can read weblogs of many Fedora contributors at our official aggregator, <ulink url="http://planet.fedoraproject.org/"></ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<xi:include href="Revision_History.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"></xi:include>
</article>

