<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="prefs">
  <title>Az asztali környezet beállítása</title>
  
  <!-- ids in this section are gradually being converted 
  to something like 'prefs-mouse'.
  remember to add an anchor for the old id in the right place -->

  <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
  <anchor id="goscustdesk-6"/>

  <!-- Desktop Overview / Desktop Preferences -->
  <anchor id="gosoverview-55"/>
  
  <!-- ids of sections removed from this document for 2.14 -->
  <anchor id="goscustdesk-10"/><!-- Customizing Your Panels -->

  <highlights>
    <para>Ez a fejezet leírja a beállítóeszközök használatát a GNOME asztali környezet személyre szabásához.</para>
  </highlights>
  <!-- move the following to its own section, "Using Pref Tools"? -->
  <para>A beállítóeszköz olyan alkalmazás, amely segítségével meg lehet változtatni a GNOME asztali környezet beállításait. Mindegyik beállítóeszköz a számítógép bizonyos szempont szerinti beállításáért felelős. Például az <application>Egér</application> beállítóeszközzel az egerét jobb vagy balkezes egérré változtathatja, vagy a kurzor sebességét állíthatja be. Az <application>Ablakok</application> beállítóeszközzel az ablakok viselkedését lehet megváltoztatni, például hogy az egér milyen módon válassza ki őket.</para>
  <para>Beállítóeszköz megnyitásához válassza a <menuchoice><guimenu>Rendszer</guimenu><guisubmenu>Beállítások</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menüpontot a felső panelből. Az almenüből válassza ki a szükséges eszközt.</para>
  <para>Néhány kivételtől eltekintve a beállítóeszközökben végrehajtott változások azonnal életbe lépnek, szükségtelen a beállítóeszköz bezárása. Ennek ablakát nyitva tarthatja addig, amíg kipróbálja a különböző lehetőségeket és további változásokat hajt végre.</para>
  <para>Néhány alkalmazás vagy rendszereszköz hozzáadhatja a saját beállítóeszközét a menühöz.</para>
  <note><para>Néhány beállítóeszköz a rendszer alapvető fontosságú részeit módosítja, ezért adminisztrátori jogokat igényel. Ilyen beállítóeszköz megnyitásakor egy párbeszédablak bekéri a jelszavát kéri. Ezek a <menuchoice><guimenu>Rendszer</guimenu><guisubmenu>Adminisztráció</guisubmenu></menuchoice> almenüben találhatók. Ez a menü összetettebb segédprogramokat is tartalmaz, amelyekkel kezelheti és frissítheti rendszerét.</para></note>


<sect1 id="prefs-personal">
  <title>Személyes</title>
  <!-- Was Login Photo prefs, could go to About Me if that was enabled by default -->
  <anchor id="goscustdesk-95"/>

  <sect2 id="goscustaccess-11">
    <title>Assistive Technologies Preferences</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>akadálymentesítés</primary>
      <secondary>akadálymentesítés beállításainak módosítása</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Assistive Technologies</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Use the <application>Assistive Technologies</application> preference tool to enable assistive technologies
in the GNOME Desktop. You can also use the <application>Assistive Technology</application> preference tool to open other preference tools which contain preferences related to assistive technologies.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><guibutton>Preferred Applications</guibutton> lets you specify assistive technology applications to start automatically when you log in. See <xref linkend="prefs-preferredapps"/></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><guibutton>Keyboard Accessibility</guibutton> lets you configure keyboard accessibility features such as sticky keys, slow keys or bounce keys.
        See <xref linkend="prefs-keyboard-a11y"/></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><guibutton>Mouse Accessibility</guibutton> lets you configure mouse accessibility features such as dwell clicking. See <xref linkend="goscustdesk-53"/></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>A <xref linkend="goscustaccess-TBL-14"/> felsorolja a módosítható akadálymentesítési beállításokat.</para>
    <table frame="topbot" id="goscustaccess-TBL-14">
      <title>Akadálymentesítés beállításai</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
        <thead>
          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry>
              <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Leírás</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Akadálymentesítés engedélyezése</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Jelölje ki ezt a beállítást az akadálymentesítés engedélyezéséhez a GNOME asztali környezetben.</para>
              <para>Note that for technical reasons, you have to log in
again after enabling this option for it to be fully effective.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="prefs-keyboard-shortcuts">
    <title>Gyorsbillentyűk beállításai</title>

    <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-39"/>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Gyorsbillentyűk</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>gyorsbillentyűk</primary>
      <secondary>beállítás</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>gyorsbillentyűk</primary>
      <secondary>beállítás</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>A <application>Gyorsbilentyűk</application> beállítóeszköz segítségével személyre szabhatja az alapértelmezett gyorsbillentyűket.</para>    
    
    <para>A <firstterm>gyorsbillentyű</firstterm> egy olyan billentyű vagy billentyűkombináció, ami alternatívát jelent a műveletek megszókott módon történő végrehajtása mellett. A gyorsbillentyűkkel kapcsolatos további információkat és a GNOME alapértelmezett gyorsbillentyűinek listáját megtalálja a <xref linkend="keyboard-skills"/> fejezetben.</para>

    <para>Gyorsbillentyű szerkesztéséhez tegye a következőket:</para>
    <orderedlist>
	    <listitem><para>Kattintson a műveletre a listában. Ha a billentyűzetet használja, a nyílbillentyűkkel navigálva válassza ki a gyorsbillentyűt és nyomja meg az <keycap>Enter</keycap> billentyűt.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Nyomja meg a művelethez rendelendő új billentyűt vagy billentyűkombinációt.</para>
	      <para>Gyorsbillentyű törléséhez nyomja meg a <keycap>Backspace</keycap> gombot. A művelet ekkor <guilabel>Tiltva</guilabel> állapotba kerül.</para>
	    </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>Gyorsbillentyű hozzárendelésének megszakításához kattintson máshová az ablakban vagy nyomja meg az <keycap>Escape</keycap> billentyűt.</para>
    
    <para>A testreszabható gyorsbillentyűk a következők szerint vannak csoportosítva:</para>
    
    <variablelist>
    	<varlistentry><term>Asztal</term>
    	  <listitem><para>Ezek általános billentyűk az egész munkaaasztal számára, mint például a kijelentkezés, <link linkend="lock-screen">a képernyő zárolása</link>, a <link linkend="menubar">panelmenü</link> megnyitása, vagy a webböngésző elindítása.</para></listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
    	<varlistentry><term>Hang</term>
    	  <listitem><para>Gyorsbillentyűk a zenelejátszó és a rendszerhangerő vezérléséhez.</para></listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
    	<varlistentry><term>Ablakkezelés</term>
    	  <listitem><para>Gyorsbillentyűk az ablakok és munkaterületek kezeléséhez, mint például a jelenlegi ablak maximalizálása vagy elmozdítása és átváltás másik munkaterületre. További információk ezekről a műveletekről a <xref linkend="windows-manipulating"/> és a <xref linkend="overview-workspaces"/> szakaszban találhatók.</para></listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>Accessibility</term>
          <listitem><para>Shortcuts for starting assistive technologies, such as
            a screen reader, a magnifier or an on-screen keyboard.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>Custom Shortcuts</term>
          <listitem><para>Custom shortcuts that have been added with the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button. This section will not be shown if there are no custom shortcuts.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      To add a custom shortcut, use the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button in the action area. You have to provide a name and a command for the new shortcut. The new custom shortcut will appear in the list of shortcuts and can be edited in the same way as the predefined shortcuts.
    </para>
    <para>
      To remove a custom shortcut, use the <guilabel>Remove</guilabel> button.
    </para>
  </sect2>  

  <sect2 id="prefs-preferredapps">
    <title>Alapértelmezett alkalmazások</title>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustdoc-2"/>       
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Alapértelmezett alkalmazások</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>alapértelmezett alkalmazások</primary>
      <see>alapértelmezett alkalmazások</see>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Use the <application>Preferred
Applications</application> preference tool to specify the applications that
you want the GNOME Desktop to use when the GNOME Desktop starts an application
for you. For example, you can specify the web browser application (<application>Epiphany
</application>, <application>Mozilla Firefox</application>, <application>Opera</application>
...) to launch when you click on a link in other applications such as 
email clients or document viewers.</para>

	<para> <application>Preferred Applications</application> can be found by going to
<menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Preferred Applications</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
    <para>A beállításokat az <application>Alapértelmezett alkalmazások</application> beállítóeszközben a következő területeken szabhatja testre.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Internet</guilabel> (Web, Mail)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Multimedia</guilabel> (Multimedia Player)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>System</guilabel> (Terminal)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> (Visual, Mobility)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>For each preferred application category, a drop-down menu contains a list of possible applications you can choose from. The list depends on the applications installed on your computer.</para>
    <para>In each category, the last item in the menu (<guimenuitem>Custom</guimenuitem>) permits you to customize the command used by the system when the specific launch action occurs.</para>
    
    <sect3 id="goscustlookandfeel-32">
      <title>Custom Command Options</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>alapértelmezett alkalmazások</primary>
        <secondary>custom command</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>The following table summarizes the various options you can choose from when you select
<guimenuitem>Custom</guimenuitem> in the drop-down application menu.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustlookandfeel-TBL-37">
        <title>Custom command options</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="18.86*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="47.14*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Parancs</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Enter the command to execute to start the custom application. For the <application>Web
Browser</application> and the <application>Mail Reader</application> applications, you can include a <literal>%s</literal>
after the command to tell the application to use the URL or Email address you clicked on. The exact command arguments
may depend on the specific application.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Run in terminal</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to run the command in a terminal window. Select this option for an
 application that does not create a window in which to run.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Execute flag (Terminal only)</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Most terminal applications have an option that cause them to treat the remaining command line options as
commands to run (<option>-x</option> for <application>gnome-terminal</application>).  Enter this option here.
 For example, this is used when executing a command of a launcher for which the chosen type is Application in Terminal.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Run at start (Accessibility only)</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to run the command as soon as your session begins. For more accessibility options, see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-access-guide?index"><citetitle>GNOME Desktop Accessibility Guide</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="prefs-look-and-feel">
	<title>Megjelenés</title>

  <sect2 id="prefs-appearance">
    <title>Appearance Preferences</title>
    <para>The <application>Appearance</application> preference tool lets
    you configure various aspects of how your desktop looks:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Theme,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Desktop Background,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fonts,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>User Interface.</para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist> 
  <sect3 id="prefs-theme">
    <title>Téma beállításai</title>
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-12"/>
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-54"/>
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-82"/>
  
    <indexterm>
      <primary>témák</primary>
      <secondary>felhasználói felület elemeinek beállításai</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>témák</primary>
      <secondary>ablakkeretek beállításai</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>témák</primary>
      <secondary>ikonok beállításai</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>ablakok</primary>
      <secondary>kerettéma beállításai</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Téma</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>A theme is a group of coordinated settings that specifies
the visual appearance of a part of the GNOME Desktop. You can choose themes
to change the appearance of the GNOME Desktop. Use the <application>Theme</application> tabbed section to select a theme. You can choose from a list
of available themes. The list of available themes includes several themes
for users with accessibility requirements. </para>
    <para>A témák a GNOME asztali környezet különböző részeire ható beállításokat tartalmaznak az alábbiak szerint:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Vezérlőelemek</term>
        <listitem>
          <para><indexterm><primary>GTK+
themes</primary><see>themes, controls options</see></indexterm><indexterm><primary>themes</primary><secondary>controls options</secondary><tertiary>introduction</tertiary></indexterm>The controls setting for a theme determines
the visual appearance of windows, panels, and applets. The controls setting
also determines the visual appearance of the GNOME-compliant interface items
that appear on windows, panels, and applets, such as menus, icons, and buttons.
Some of the controls setting options that are available are designed for special
accessibility needs. You can choose an option for the controls setting from
the <guilabel>Controls</guilabel> tabbed section in the <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> window.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Colors</term>
        <listitem>
           <para><indexterm><primary>themes</primary><secondary>color options</secondary><tertiary>introduction</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>color themes</primary><see>themes, color options</see></indexterm>The color setting for
a theme determines the color of various user interface elements. You can choose several pairs of colors from the <guilabel>Colors</guilabel> tabbed section in the <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> window.</para>
           <note><para>It is important to choose pairs of colors that have a good contrast with each other,
           otherwise text may become hard to read.</para></note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Window frame</term>
        <listitem>
          <para><indexterm><primary>themes</primary><secondary>window frame options</secondary><tertiary>introduction</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Metacity themes</primary><see>themes, window frame options</see></indexterm>The window frame setting for
a theme determines the appearance of the frames around windows only. You can
choose an option for the window frame setting from the <guilabel>Window Border</guilabel> tabbed section in the <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> window.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Icons</term>
        <listitem>
          <para><indexterm><primary>themes</primary><secondary>icons options</secondary><tertiary>introduction</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>icon themes</primary><see>themes, icons options</see></indexterm>The icon setting for a theme determines the appearance of
the icons on panels and the desktop background. You can choose an option for
the icon setting from the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel> tabbed section in the <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> window.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pointer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para><indexterm><primary>themes</primary><secondary>pointer options</secondary><tertiary>introduction</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>pointer themes</primary><see>themes, pointer options</see></indexterm>The pointer setting for a theme determines the appearance of
and sice of the mouse pointer. You can choose an options for the pointer setting fromthe <guilabel>Pointer</guilabel> tabbed section in the <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> window.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <sect4 id="goscustdesk-61">
      <title>Egyéni téma létrehozása</title>
      <para>The themes that are listed in the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel>
tabbed section are different combinations of controls options, window frame options,
and icon options. You can create a custom theme that uses different combinations
of controls options, window frame options, and icon options.</para>
      <para>Egyéni téma létrehozásához tegye a következőket:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool.
          Open the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tabbed section.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Válasszon ki egy témát a témalistából.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Customize</guibutton> button. A <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the controls option that you want to use in the custom
theme from the list in the <guilabel>Controls</guilabel> tabbed section. The
list of available controls options includes several options for users with
accessibility requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guilabel>Window Border</guilabel> tab to display
the <guilabel>Window Border</guilabel> tabbed section. Select the window frame
option that you want to use in the custom theme from the list of available
options. The list of available window frame options includes several options
for users with accessibility requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel> tab to display the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel> tabbed section. Select the icons option that you want to
use in the custom theme from the list of available options. The list of available
icons options includes several options for users with accessibility requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to close the <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>On the <application>Appearance</application> preferences tool,
click on the <guibutton>Save As</guibutton> button. A <guilabel>Save Theme
As</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Adja meg az egyéni téma nevét és rövid leírását, majd kattintson a <guibutton>Mentés</guibutton> gombra. Az egyéni téma ezek után megjelenik az elérhető témák között.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect4>
    <sect4 id="goscustdesk-62">
      <title>Új téma telepítése</title>
      <para>A meglévő témákhoz újakat adhat hozzá. Az új témának tarral és gzippel csomagolt archívumban, azaz egy <filename>.tar.gz</filename> kiterjesztésű fájlban kell lennie.</para>
      <para>Új téma telepítéséhez tegye a következőket:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool.
           Open the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tabbed section.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Install</guibutton> button.
A file chooser dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the location of the theme archive file in the location
entry. Alternatively, select the theme archive file in the file list. When you have selected the file, click <guibutton>Open</guibutton>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Az új téma telepítéséhez kattintson a <guibutton>Telepítés</guibutton> gombra.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect4>

<!--How does this work nowadays ?
    <sect4 id="goscustdesk-80">
      <title>To Install a New Theme Option</title>
      <para>You can install new controls options, window frame options, or icons
options. You can find many controls options on the Internet.</para>
      <para>To install a new controls option, window frame option, or icons option,
perform the following steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool.
          Open the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tabbed section.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Customize</guibutton> button.
An <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the tab for the type of theme that you want to install.
For example, to install an icons option, click on the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel>
tab.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Install Theme</guibutton> button.
A <guilabel>Theme Installation</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the location of the option archive file in the drop-down
combination box. Alternatively, to browse for the file, click on the <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button. When you have selected the file, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Install</guibutton> button to install
the new option. </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect4>
-->
    <sect4 id="goscustdesk-81">
      <title>To Delete a Theme Option</title>
      <para>You can delete controls options, window frame options, or icons options.</para>
      <para>To delete a controls option, window frame option, or icons option, perform
the following steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool.
          Open the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tabbed section.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Customize</guibutton> button.
A <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the tab for the type of option that you want to delete. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the theme option you want to delete.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button to delete the
          selected option. Note that you can not delete system-wide theme
          options.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect4>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="prefs-desktopbackground">
    <title>Asztal hátterének beállításai</title>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-7"/>       
    <indexterm>
      <primary>asztal</primary>
      <secondary>háttér testreszabása</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>A GNOME asztali környezet beállítóeszközei</primary>
      <see>beállítóeszközök</see>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Háttér</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>hátterek</primary>
      <secondary>asztal hátterének testreszabása</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The <link linkend="overview-desktop">desktop</link> background is the image or color that is applied to your
desktop. You can open <guilabel>Background</guilabel> tabbed section in the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool by right-clicking on the desktop and choosing <guimenuitem>Change Desktop Background</guimenuitem>, as well as from the <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menu.</para>
    <para>Az asztal hátterét a következő módon lehet beállítani:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Válasszon ki egy képet az asztal hátterének. A kép a háttérszín fölé kerül. A háttérszín láthatóvá válik, ha átlátszó képet választ, vagy ha az nem fedi le a teljes asztalt.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Válassza ki az asztal háttérszínét. Választhat homogén színt, de két szín közötti színátmenetet is létrehozható. A színátmenet jelentése, hogy az egyik szín fokozatosan átmegy a másikba.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <tip><para>Egy színt vagy mintát a <application>Nautilus</application> fájlböngészőben található <link linkend="nautilus-backgrounds-and-emblems"><guilabel>Hátterek és matricák</guilabel>párbeszédablakból</link> is behúzhat az asztalra.</para></tip>
    <para>A <xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-14"/> felsorolja az asztal hátterének módosítható beállításait.</para>
    <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-14">
      <title>Asztal hátterének beállításai</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="18.86*"/>
        <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="47.14*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
              <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
            </entry>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
              <para>Leírás</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guibutton>Desktop Background</guibutton>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>Choose an image from the list.  Alternately, you can use the
<guibutton>Add</guibutton> button to choose any image on your computer.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Stílus</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>A kép megjelenésének meghatározásához válasszon az alábbi lehetőségek közül a <guilabel>Stílus</guilabel> lenyíló menüből:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Középre helyezett</guilabel>: A kép az asztal közepén jelenik meg, figyelembe véve a kép eredeti méretét.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Képernyő kitöltése</guilabel>: Kinagyítja a képet, hogy az elfedje az asztalt, szükség esetén módosítva a kép arányait.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Kifeszített</guilabel>: méretarányosan megnöveli a kép méretét, hogy a kép a képernyő széleit elérje, miközben fenntartja a kép arányait.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Nagyítás</guilabel>: megnöveli a kép kisebb dimenzióját, hogy a kép a képernyő széleit elérje, miközben a kép másik dimenziója levágásra kerülhet.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Tiled</guilabel>: Duplicates the original-sized image as
often as necessary and print the images next to another so as they entirely cover the desktop.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Add</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para/>
              <para>Click on the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> to browse for
an image on your computer.  A standard file selector will be presented.  Choose
the image you want and click <guibutton>Open</guibutton>.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Eltávolítás</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>Choose the image that you want to remove,
then click <guilabel>Remove</guilabel>.  This removes the image from the list of available wallpapers; however, it does not delete the image from your computer.
</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Colors</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>To specify a color scheme, use  the options
in the <guilabel>Style</guilabel> drop-down list, and the color
selector buttons.</para>
              <para>A színséma a következő módszerek egyikével adható meg:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A <guilabel>Háttér stílusa</guilabel> legördülő listából válassza a <guilabel>Homogén szín</guilabel> beállítást, ekkor az asztal háttere egyszínű lesz.</para>
                  <para>A kívánt szín kiválasztásához kattintson a <guibutton>Szín</guibutton> gombra. Megjelenik a <guilabel>Szín kiválasztása</guilabel> párbeszédablak. Válasszon ki egy színt, majd nyomja meg az <guibutton>OK</guibutton> gombot.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A <guilabel>Háttér stílusa</guilabel> legördülő listából válassza ki a <guilabel>Vízszintes színátmenet</guilabel> beállítást, ekkor a képernyő bal és jobb széle között színátmenet jön létre.</para>
                  <para>Kattintson a <guibutton>Bal oldali szín</guibutton> gombra a <guilabel>Szín kiválasztása</guilabel> párbeszédablak megjelenítéséhez, majd válassza ki a bal szélen megjelenítendő színt.</para>
                  <para>Kattintson a <guibutton>Jobb oldali szín</guibutton> gombra, majd válassza ki a jobb szélen megjelenítendő színt.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A <guilabel>Háttér stílusa</guilabel> legördülő listából válassza a <guilabel>Függőleges színátmenet</guilabel> beállítást, ekkor a képernyő felső és alsó széle között színátmenet jön létre.</para>
                  <para>Kattintson a <guibutton>Felső szín</guibutton> gombra a <guilabel>Szín kiválasztása</guilabel> párbeszédablak megjelenítéséhez, majd válassza ki a felső szélen megjelenítendő színt.</para>
                  <para>Kattintson az <guibutton>Alsó szín</guibutton> gombra, majd válassza ki az alsó szélen megjelenítendő színt.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="prefs-font">
    <title>Betűkészlet beállításai</title>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-38"/>
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-83"/>
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-94"/>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Betűkészlet</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>betűkészletek</primary>
      <secondary>asztal</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>betűkészletek</primary>
      <secondary>alkalmazások</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>betűkészletek</primary>
      <secondary>ablak címe</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>betűkészletek</primary>
      <secondary>terminál</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>betűkészletek</primary>
      <secondary>megjelenítés</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Use the <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> tabbed section in the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool
to choose which fonts are used in different parts of the desktop, and the way in which fonts are displayed on the screen.</para>

    <sect4 id="prefs-font-choose">
      <title>Betűkészletek kiválasztása</title>
      <para>A betűkészlet-választó gomb megjeleníti a betűkészlet nevét és méretét. A név megjelenhet félkövér, dőlt, és szabályos stílusban.</para>
      <para>A betűkészlet megváltoztatásához kattintson a betűkészlet-választó gombra. Megjelenik a betűkészlet-választó párbeszédablak. Válassza ki a betűkészletcsaládot, -stílust, és -méretet a listából. Az előnézeti rész megjeleníti a jelenlegi választás előnézetét. Az <guibutton>OK</guibutton> gombra kattintva elfogadhatja a választást és frissítheti az asztalt.</para>
      <para>Az asztal következő részeihez választhat betűkészletet:</para>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term><guilabel>Alkalmazás betűkészlete</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para>Ez a betűkészlet az alkalmazások menüjében, eszköztárában és párbeszédablakaiban jelenik meg.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
      	<varlistentry>
      	  <term><guilabel>Dokumentum betűkészlete</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para>Ez a betűkészlet az alkalmazásokban lévő dokumentumokat jeleníti meg.</para>
      	    <note><para>Néhány alkalmazásban ezt a beállítást felül lehet írni az alkalmazás Beállítások párbeszédablakában.</para></note>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term><guilabel>Asztal betűkészlete</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para>Ez a betűkészlet az asztalon lévő ikonok nevében kerül felhasználásra.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term><guilabel>Ablak címsorának betűkészlete</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para>Ez a betűkészlet az ablakok címsorában kerül felhasználásra.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term><guilabel>Rögzített szélességű betűkészlet</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para>Ez a betűkészlet a <application>Terminál</application> alkalmazásban és a programozáshoz használt alkalmazásokban használatos.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
      	</variablelist>
  	</sect4>
	
  	<sect4 id="prefs-font-rendering">
      <title>Betűmegjelenítés</title>
      <para>A betűkészlet képernyőn való megjelenítésével kapcsolatban a következő beállításokat választhatja:</para>
	
    	<variablelist>
     	<varlistentry>
    	  <term><guilabel>Rendering</guilabel></term>
    	  <listitem>
    	    <para>A betűk képernyőn történő megjelenítése az alábbi beállításokkal befolyásolható:</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Fekete-fehér</guilabel>: a betűk fekete-fehérben jelennek meg. A karakterek széle bizonyos esetekben recésnek tűnhet, mert nincs élsimítás. <firstterm>Élsimításnak</firstterm> nevezik azt a módszert, melynek karakterek körvonalára történő alkalmazásával a karakter vonalai simábbak lesznek.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>A legszebb betűforma</guilabel>: a betűk élsimítása, ahol csak lehet. Használja ezt a beállítást a katódsugárcsöves monitorokhoz.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>A legjobb kontraszt</guilabel>: A lehető legélesebb kontraszt eléréséhez módosítja a betűkészletet, valamint a betűk élsimítását is elvégzi, így a karaktereknek sima szélük lesz. Ez a beállítás fokozhatja a GNOME asztali környezet akadálymentességét a látássérült felhasználók számára.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Simítás a képponton belül (LCD)</guilabel>: kihasználja az egyes LCD képpontok alakját a betűkészlet simább megjelenítéséhez. Használja ezt a beállítást LCD vagy laposképernyős monitorokhoz.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
    	  </listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
     	<varlistentry>
    	  <term><guibutton>Részletek</guibutton></term>
    	  <listitem>
    	    <para>A gombra kattintva további beállítások adhatók meg a betűk megjelenítésével kapcsolatban.</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Felbontás (pont/hüvelyk)</guilabel>: itt adható meg a képernyő felbontása, amelyet a betűk megjelenítésénél figyelembe kell venni.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Simítás</guilabel>: válassza ki az egyik élsimítási módszert.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Hinting</guilabel>: A <firstterm>hinting</firstterm> az a betűmegjelenítési technológia, amely javítja a betűk képét kis méretű vagy alacsony felbontású képernyőn történő megjelenítésnél. Válassza ki az egyik lehetőséget a hinting módjának meghatározásához.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Sorrend a képponton belül</guilabel>: válassza ki az egyik lehetőséget a képponton belüli színsorrend megadásához. Ez a beállítás folyadékkristályos vagy lapos képernyőkön használható.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
    	  </listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   
    </sect4>
<!-- go to fonts folder no longer exists
    <sect4 id="goscustdesk-83">
      <title>Previewing a Font</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>fonts</primary>
        <secondary>previewing</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>A preview of a font shows the characters of a font at different sizes, as well as copyright and technical information. To preview a font, perform the following steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Font</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the top panel.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click on <guibutton>Details</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click on <guibutton>Go to font folder</guibutton>. The <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> folder opens.</para></listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open a font to display a preview.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect4>
-->

<!-- go to fonts folder no longer exists
    <sect4 id="goscustdesk-94">
      <title>Adding a TrueType Font</title>
      <para>To add a TrueType font to your system, perform the following steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open the <application>Font</application> preference tool by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Font</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the panel menubar.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click on <guibutton>Details</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click on <guibutton>Go to font folder</guibutton>. The <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> folder opens.</para></listitem>      
        <listitem>
          <para>Open a file manager window and select the TrueType font that
you want to add.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Copy the TrueType font file that you want to add to the <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> folder.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <warning><para>The new font will not appear in the <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> folder until you next log in. You will need to relaunch applications for them to have access to the new font. These are known bugs in Gnome.</para></warning>
      
      <tip><para>You can also open the <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> folder by typing the following URI into <application>Nautilus</application> file manager's <link linkend="nautilus-open-location">Open Location dialog</link>: <command>fonts:///</command>.</para></tip>
    </sect4>
-->
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="prefs-menustoolbars">
    <title>Interface Preferences</title>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustuserinter-2"/>    
    <indexterm>
      <primary>eszköztárak, megjelenés testreszabása</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Menük és eszköztárak</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>menük</primary>
      <secondary>alkalmazásokban, megjelenés testreszabása</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>You can use the <guilabel>Interface</guilabel> tabbed section in the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool to customize the appearance
of menus, menubars, and toolbars for applications that are part of GNOME.</para>
    <para>A beállítások változtatásával az előnézeti kép frissül az ablakban. Ennek segítségével megtekintheti a változásokat akkor is, ha éppen egy alkalmazás sincs nyitva.</para>
    <variablelist>
     	<varlistentry>
    	  <term><guilabel>Ikonok megjelenítése a menükben</guilabel></term>
    	  <listitem>
    	    <para>Válassza ki ezt a beállítást egy ikon megjelenítéséhez a menüpontok mellett az alkalmazásokban és a panelmenüben. Nem minden menüpont rendelkezik ikonnal.</para>
    	  </listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
    	<varlistentry>
    	  <term><guilabel>Editable menu shortcut keys</guilabel></term>
	      <listitem><para>Ezen beállítás kiválasztásával szerkesztheti a menüpontokra vonatkozó gyorsbillentyűket.</para>
	      <para>Egy alkalmazás gyorsbillentyűjének megváltoztatásához nyisson meg egy menüt, vigye az egérkurzort a megváltoztatni kívánt menüpont fölé és nyomja le az új billentyűkombinációt. A gyorsbillentyű eltávolításához nyomja meg a <keycap>Backspace</keycap> vagy a <keycap>Delete</keycap> billentyűt.</para>
	      <warning>
	        <para>Ennek a szolgáltatásnak a használatakor a rendszer nem figyelmezteti, ha egy új gyorsbillentyű hozzárendelése törli egy másik parancs gyorsbillentyűjét.</para>
	        <para>Nincs lehetőség a parancs eredeti, alapértelmezett gyorsbillentyűjének helyreállítására.</para>
	        <para>Ez a szolgáltatás nem vonatkozik azokra a gyorsbillentyűkre, melyek általánosak az alkalmazásokban, mint például a másolás parancs gyorsbillentyűje a <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>. Ez ellentmondásokhoz vezethetne a GNOME alkalmazásokban.</para>
	      </warning>
	      </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     	<varlistentry>
    	  <term><guilabel>Eszköztárgombok címkéi</guilabel></term>
    	  <listitem>
    	    <para>Az alábbi lehetőségek egyikének kiválasztásával megadhatja, hogy mi jelenjen meg a GNOME alkalmazások eszköztárain:</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Szöveg az ikonok alatt</guilabel>: válassza ezt a lehetőséget, ha minden gombon szöveget és ikont szeretne látni.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Szöveg az ikonok mellett</guilabel>: válassza ki ezt a lehetőséget, ha minden gombon ikont szeretne látni és a legfontosabbak mellett szöveget is.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Csak ikonok</guilabel>: válassza ezt a lehetőséget, ha az eszköztárak gombjain csak ikonokat szeretne látni.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Csak szöveg</guilabel>: válassza ezt a lehetőséget, ha az eszköztárak gombjain csak szöveget szeretne látni.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
    	  </listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="prefs-windows">
    <title>Windows Preferences</title>

    <!-- preserve for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-58"/>    

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ablakkezelő</primary>
      <secondary>személyre szabás</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Ablakok</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Use the <application>Windows</application>
preference tool to customize window behavior for the GNOME Desktop.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="goscustwindows-TBL-14"/> lists the windows preferences
that you can modify.</para>
    <table frame="topbot" id="goscustwindows-TBL-14">
      <title>Windows Preferences</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="18.86*"/>
        <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="47.14*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
              <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
            </entry>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
              <para>Leírás</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Ablakok kiválasztása, ha az egér föléjük ér</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>Jelölje be ezt a lehetőséget, ha azt szeretné, hogy az ablak akkor kapja meg a fókuszt, ha az egérmutatóval rámutat. Az ablak megtartja a fókuszt, amíg az egérmutatót más ablak fölé nem viszi.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Kijelölt ablakok előtérbe hozásának késleltetése</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>Jelölje be ezt a négyzetet, ha azt szeretné, hogy az ablak a fókusz megkapása után csak bizonyos idővel jöjjön fel az előtérbe.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Késleltetés az előtérbe hozás előtt</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>Adja meg a fókusz megkapása és az előtérbe hozás közötti késleltetés idejét.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Kattintson duplán a címsoron a művelet végrehajtásához:</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>Válassza ki az ablak címsorán történő dupla kattintás által kiváltott műveletet. Válasszon a következő lehetőségek közül:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Maximalizálás</guilabel>: a legnagyobb méretre nagyítja az ablakot.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Maximize Vertically</guilabel>: Maximizes the window vertically without changing its width.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Maximize Horizontally</guilabel>: Maximizes the window horizontally without changing its height.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Minimize</guilabel>: Minimizes the window.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Felgördítés:</guilabel> Az ablak felgördítése a címsorra.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>None</guilabel>: Do nothing.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
              <para>If a window is already maximized or rolled up, double-clicking 
              on the titlebar will return it to its normal state.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Az ablak áthelyezéséhez tartsa lenyomva ezt a billentyűt, és húzza el az ablakot</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>Válassza ki azt a billentyűt, amelyet lenyomva kell tartani az ablak áthelyezéséhez.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <note>
      <para>The position of the Control, Alt and Super keys on the keyboard can be modified in the 
      Keyboard Layout Options dialog, see <xref linkend="prefs-keyboard-layoutoptions"/>. 
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="prefs-screensaver">
    <title>Screensaver Preferences</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>képernyővédő</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>A <firstterm>screensaver</firstterm> displays moving images on your screen when your computer is not being used. Screensavers also help prevent older monitors being damaged by the same image being displayed for long periods of time. To stop the screensaver and return to the desktop, move the mouse or press a key on the keyboard.</para>
    <para>Use the <application>Screensaver</application> preference tool to set the type of screensaver, the time before the screensaver starts, and whether to require a password to return to the desktop.</para>
    <para>You can modify the following settings:</para>
    <variablelist>
    	<varlistentry>
    	  <term>Screensaver</term>
    	  <listitem><para>Select the <guilabel>Screensaver theme</guilabel> from the list. A reduced version of the selected screensaver theme is shown. Press <guibutton>Preview</guibutton> to show the selected theme on the whole screen. During preview, use the arrow buttons at the top of the screen to go through the list of screensaver themes.</para>
    	  <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem><para>The <guilabel>Blank screen</guilabel> theme displays no image and only shows a black screen.</para></listitem>
	        <listitem><para>The <guilabel>Random</guilabel> theme selects a screensaver to display from the list at random.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    	  <para>Which screensavers are shown in the remainder of the list depends on your distributor or vendor.</para></listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
    	<varlistentry>
    	  <term>Regard the computer as idle after...</term>
    	  <listitem><para>Your computer becomes idle after this amount of time has passed with no input from you, such as moving the mouse or typing. This may affect power management (the monitor may power down for example) or instant messaging (chat applications may set your status as "away"). Use the slider to set the length of time in minutes or hours.</para></listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
    	<varlistentry>
    	  <term>Activate screensaver when computer is idle</term>
    	  <listitem><para>Select this option to have the screensaver start after the set length of time. </para></listitem>
    	</varlistentry>
    	<varlistentry>
    	  <term>Lock screen when screensaver is active</term>
    	  <listitem><para>When this option is selected, the screensaver will prompt you for your password when you try to return to the desktop. For more on locking your screen, see <xref linkend="lock-screen"/>.</para></listitem>  	
    	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="prefs-internet-and-network">
	<title>Internet and Network</title>

  <sect2 id="prefs-network-admin">
 	<title>Network Settings</title>

    <para>The <application>Network Settings</application> allows you to specify the way your system connects to other computers and to internet.</para>
    <para>You will be prompted for the administrator password when you start <application>Network Settings</application>. This is because the changes done with this tool will affect the whole system.</para>

  <sect3 id="prefs-network-admin-getting-started">
    <title>Getting started</title>



    <para>The <application>Network Settings</application> main window contains four tabbed sections:</para>

    <variablelist>
	 <varlistentry>
	   <term><guilabel>Connections</guilabel></term>
	   <listitem>
		<para>Shows all network interfaces, it also allows you to modify their settings.</para>
	   </listitem>
	 </varlistentry>

	 <varlistentry>
	   <term><guilabel>Általános</guilabel></term>
	   <listitem>
		<para>Allows you to modify your system host name and domain name.</para>
	   </listitem>
	 </varlistentry>

    	 <varlistentry>
	   <term><guilabel>DNS</guilabel></term>
	   <listitem>
		<para>Contains two sections, the <guilabel>DNS servers</guilabel> are what your computer use for resolving the IP addresses from the domain names. The <guilabel>search domains</guilabel> are the default domains in which your system will search any host when no domain is specified.</para>
	   </listitem>
	 </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	   <term><guilabel>Hosts</guilabel></term>
	   <listitem>
		<para>Shows the list of aliases for accessing other computers.</para>
	   </listitem>
	 </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="prefs-network-admin-usage">
    <title>Használat</title>

    <sect4 id="tool-modify-connection">
	 <title>To modify a connection settings</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>Connections</guilabel> section, select the interface you want to modify and press the <guilabel>Properties</guilabel> button, depending on the interface type you will be able to modify different data.</para>

	 <variablelist>
	   <varlistentry>
		<term>Ethernet and IRLAN interfaces</term>
		<listitem>
		  <para>You can modify the way the interface is configured (DHCP or manually), if the interface is configured manually, you can also modify the interface IP address, netmask and gateway.</para>
		</listitem>
	   </varlistentry>

	   <varlistentry>
		<term>Wireless interfaces</term>
		<listitem>
		  <para>You can modify the way the interface is configured (DHCP or manually), if the interface is configured manually, you can also modify the interface IP address, netmask and gateway, you can also modify the network name (ESSID) for this interface.</para>
		</listitem>
	   </varlistentry>

	   <varlistentry>
		<term>Parallel line interfaces</term>
		<listitem>
		  <para>You can modify the interface IP address, as well as the remote IP address.</para>
		</listitem>
	   </varlistentry>

	   <varlistentry>
		<term>PPP/Modem interfaces</term>
		<listitem>
		  <para>You can modify the modem device, whether you want it to dial using tones or pulses, the modem volume, the phone number, the username and password that your ISP provided and other advanced settings for PPP.</para>
		</listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	 </variablelist>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To activate or deactivate an interface</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>Connections</guilabel> section, enable or disable the checkbox beside the interface.</para>
    </sect4>
    
    <sect4>
	 <title>To change your host name and domain name</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>General</guilabel> section, change the hostname or domain name text boxes.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To add a new domain name server</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>DNS Servers</guilabel> section, press the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button and fill in the new list row with the new domain name server.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To delete a domain name server</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>DNS Servers</guilabel> section, select a DNS IP address from the list and press the <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> button.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To add a new search domain</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>Search Domains</guilabel> section, press the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button and fill in the new list row with the new search domain.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To delete a search domain</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>Search Domains</guilabel> section, select a search domain from the list and press the <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> button.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To add a new host alias</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>Hosts</guilabel> section, press the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button and type an IP address and the aliases that will point to in the window that pops up.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To modify a host alias</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>Hosts</guilabel> section, select an alias, press the <guilabel>Properties</guilabel> button from the list and modify the alias settings in the window that pops up.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To delete a host alias</title>
	 <para>In the <guilabel>Hosts</guilabel> section, select an alias from the list and press the <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> button.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="prefs-network-admin-add-new-profile">
	 <title>To save your current network configuration as a "Location"</title>
	 <para>Press the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button besides the <guilabel>Locations</guilabel> menu, specify the location name in the window that pops up.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To delete a location</title>
	 <para>Press the <guilabel>Remove</guilabel> button besides the <guilabel>Locations</guilabel> menu, the selected profile will be deleted.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
	 <title>To switch to a location</title>
	 <para>Select one location from the <guilabel>Locations</guilabel> menu, all the configuration will be switched automatically to the chosen location.</para>
    </sect4>

	</sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="prefs-networkproxy">
    <title>Network Proxy Preferences</title>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-50"/>       
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Hálózati proxy</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>hálózati proxy</primary>
      <secondary>beállítások</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Hálózat</primary>
      <secondary>configuring connection</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>proxy</primary>
      <secondary>beállítások</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The <application>Network Proxy Preferences</application>
    enables you to configure how your system connects to the Internet.</para>
    <para>You can configure the GNOME Desktop to connect to a <firstterm>proxy server</firstterm>,
    and specify the details of the proxy server. A proxy server is a server that intercepts requests
    to another server, and fulfills the request itself, if it can. You can enter the domain name or
    the Internet Protocol (IP) address of the proxy server. A <firstterm>domain name</firstterm> is
    a unique alphabetic identifier for a computer on a network. An <firstterm>IP address</firstterm>
    is a unique numeric identifier for a computer on a network.</para>
    <remark>Why would one want to use a proxy?  This description makes it sounds like it's
    a user preference, rather than being dictated by the network you're on.  We should make
    this more clear.</remark>
    <para>Since it is possible that you need to use a different proxy configuration in different places,
    <application>Network Proxy Preferences</application> allows you to define separate proxy configurations
    and switch between them using the <guilabel>Location</guilabel> drop-down box at the top of the window.
    Choose <guilabel>New Location</guilabel> to create a proxy configuration for a new location. Locations
    can be removed using the <guilabel>Delete Location</guilabel> button at the bottom of the window.</para>
  
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Közvetlen internetkapcsolat</guilabel></term>
        <listitem><para>Select this option to connect to the Internet without a proxy server.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Kézi proxybeállítás</guilabel></term>
        <listitem><para>Select this option to connect to the Internet through a proxy server and
        configure the proxy settings manually.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>HTTP proxy</guilabel></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Enter the domain name or IP address of the proxy server to use when you request
              an HTTP service. Enter the port number of the HTTP service on the proxy server in the
              <guilabel>Port</guilabel> field.</para>
              <para>If the HTTP proxy server requires authentication, click the <guibutton>Details</guibutton>
              button to enter your username and password.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>Biztonságos HTTP proxy</guilabel></term>
            <listitem><para>Enter the domain name or IP address of the proxy server to use when you
            request a secure HTTP service. Enter the port number of the secure HTTP service on
            the proxy server in the <guilabel>Port</guilabel> field.</para></listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>FTP proxy</guilabel></term>
            <listitem><para>Enter the domain name or IP address of the proxy server to use when you
            request an FTP service. Enter the port number of the FTP service on the proxy server in
            the <guilabel>Port</guilabel> field.</para></listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>Socks kiszolgáló</guilabel></term>
            <listitem><para>Enter the domain name or IP address of the Socks host to use. Enter the port
            number for the Socks protocol on the proxy server in the <guilabel>Port</guilabel> field.</para></listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term><guilabel>Automatikus proxybeállítás</guilabel></term><listitem><para>Akkor válassza ezt a lehetőséget, ha proxykiszolgálón keresztül csatlakozik az internetre, és automatikusan szeretné beállítani a proxykiszolgálót.</para>
      <para>Automatic proxy configuration works by means of a so-called PAC file, which your browser downloads from a web server. If you don't specify the URL for a PAC file in the <guilabel>Autoconfiguration URL</guilabel> entry, your browser 
      will try to locate one automatically.</para>
      <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term><guilabel>Autokonfigurációs URL</guilabel></term><listitem><para>Enter the URL of a PAC file that contains the information required to configure the proxy
    server automatically.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
      </variablelist></listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    
    <para>Set which hosts should not use the proxy in the <guilabel>Ignore Host List</guilabel> in the <guilabel>Ignored Hosts</guilabel> tabbed section. When you access these hosts, you will connect to the Internet directly without a proxy.</para>
    
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="prefs-remotedesktop">
    <title>Remote Desktop Preferences</title>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustdesk-90"/>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>setting session sharing preferences</primary>
    </indexterm>           
    <para>The <application>Remote Desktop</application> preference tool enables you to share a GNOME Desktop session
between multiple users, and to set session-sharing preferences.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-91"/> lists the session-sharing preferences
that you can set. These preferences have a direct impact on the security of
your system.</para>
    <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-91">
      <title>Session Sharing Preferences</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="colspec18" colwidth="19.21*"/>
        <colspec colname="colspec19" colwidth="46.79*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
              <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
            </entry>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
              <para>Leírás</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Allow other
users to view your desktop</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>Select this option to enable remote users to view your
session. All keyboard, pointer, and clipboard events from the remote user
are ignored.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Allow other
users to control your desktop</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
              <para>Select this option to enable other to access and control
your session from a remote location.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <!--
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Users
can view your desktop using this command:</guilabel>
                
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>Click on the command text to send it to
another user by email.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          -->
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>
                <guilabel>When
a user tries to view or control your desktop</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>Select the following security
considerations when a user tries to view or control your session:<itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Ask you for confirmation:</guilabel> Select this
option if you want remote users to ask you for confirmation when they want
to share your session. This option enables you to be aware of other users
who connect to your session. You can also decide what time is suitable for
the remote user to connect to your session.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Require the user to enter this password:</guilabel>
Select this option to authenticate the remote user if authentication is used.
This option provides an extra level of security.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Password</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
              <para>Enter the password that the client who attempts to view or control your session
must enter.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect2>  

</sect1>


<sect1 id="prefs-hardware">
	<title>Hardware</title>

  <sect2 id="prefs-keyboard">
    <title>Keyboard Preferences</title>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustperiph-2"/>       
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Billentyűzet</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>billentyűzet</primary>
      <secondary>általános beállítások</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Use the <application>Keyboard</application> preference tool to modify the autorepeat preferences for
your keyboard, and to configure typing break settings. </para>
    <!--
    adds no information until each tab can be briefly summarized.
    
    <para>You can set the preferences for the <application>Keyboard</application>
preference tool in the following functional areas:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Keyboard</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Typing Break</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Layouts</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Layout Options</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    -->
    <para>To open the <link linkend="prefs-keyboard-a11y"><application>Keyboard <emphasis>Accessibility</emphasis></application> preference tool</link>, click the <guibutton>Accessibility</guibutton> button.</para>    
    <sect3 id="goscustdesk-40">
      <title>Keyboard Preferences</title>
      <para>Use the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tabbed section to set general
keyboard preferences.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustperiph-TBL-3"/> lists the keyboard preferences
that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustperiph-TBL-3">
        <title>Keyboard Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="colspec18" colwidth="19.21*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec19" colwidth="46.79*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Key presses
repeat when key is held down</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>A billentyűismétlés engedélyezéséhez jelölje be ezt a négyzetet. Ha a billentyűismétlés engedélyezve van, egy billentyű lenyomása és nyomva tartása a billentyűhöz rendelt művelet ismételt végrehajtását fogja eredményezni. Ha például egy betű billentyűjét lenyomja és nyomva tartja, a betű ismétlődően beíródik.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Késleltetés</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Adja meg a billentyű lenyomása és az ismétlés kezdete közötti késleltetési időt.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Sebesség</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Adja meg a művelet ismétlésének sebességét.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Cursor blinks in text boxes and fields</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Jelölje be ezt a négyzetet, ha villogó kurzort szeretne látni a szövegdobozokban és a beviteli mezőkben.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Sebesség</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>A csúszka segítségével a villogás frekvenciája adható meg.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Beállítások kipróbálása</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>A tesztterület egy interaktív felület, ahol láthatja, hogy a billentyűzet beállításai hogyan hatnak gépeléskor a megjelenítésre. Gépeljen a tesztterületre a beállítások hatásainak teszteléséhez.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="prefs-keyboard-layouts">
      <title>Keyboard Layouts Preferences</title>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor id="goscustdesk-100"/>         
      <para>Use the <guilabel>Layouts</guilabel> tabbed section to set your keyboard's language, and also the make and model of keyboard you are using.</para>
      <para>This will allow GNOME to make use of special media keys on your keyboard, and to show the correct characters for your keyboard's language.</para>
      
      <variablelist>
	      <varlistentry>
	        <term><guilabel>Keyboard model</guilabel></term>
	        <listitem><para>Use the browse button (labelled with the currently selected keyboard model) to choose another keyboard make and model.</para></listitem>
	      </varlistentry>
	      <varlistentry>
	        <term><guilabel>Separate layout for each window</guilabel></term>
	        <listitem><para>
	        When this option is selected, each window has its own keyboard layout. Changing to a different layout will only affect the current window.</para>
	        <para>This allows you to to type with a Russian keyboard layout in a word processor, then switch to your web browser and type with an English keyboard layout, for example. </para></listitem>
              </varlistentry>
	      <varlistentry>
	        <term><guilabel>Selected Layouts</guilabel></term>
	        <listitem><para>You can switch between selected layouts to change the characters your keyboard produces when you type. To add a layout, click <guibutton>Add</guibutton>. You can have up to four layouts. To remove a layout, select it and press <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>.</para>
	        <para>To switch between keyboard layouts, use the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gswitchit"><application>Keyboard Indicator</application> panel applet</ulink>. </para>
                 <para>To add a layout to the list of selected layouts, click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button. It opens a layout chooser dialog, which lets you select a layout by country or by language.</para> 
	        </listitem>
	      </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      
      <para>Click <guibutton>Reset to Defaults</guibutton> to restore all keyboard layout settings to their initial state for your system and locale.</para>

      <para>Click the <guibutton>Layout Options</guibutton> button to open the <guilabel>Keyboard Layout Options</guilabel> dialog.</para>
   </sect3>
    
    <sect3 id="prefs-keyboard-layoutoptions"> 
      <title>Keyboard Layout Options</title>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor id="goscustdesk-101"/>
      <para>The <guilabel>Keyboard Layout Options</guilabel> dialog has options for the behaviour of keyboard modifier keys and certain shortcut options.</para>
      <para>Expand each group label to show the available options. A label in boldface indicates that the options in the group have been changed from the default setting.</para>
      <note><para>The options shown in this dialog depend on the X windowing system you are using. Not all the following options might be listed on your system, and not all the options shown might work on your system.</para></note>

      <!-- the options of mystery!!!       
           for future reference, these are in
           /etc/X11/xkb/rules/xorg.xml
      -->
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Adding the EuroSign to certain keys</guilabel></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Use these options to add the Euro currency symbol € to a key as a third-level character. To access this symbol, you must assign a <guilabel>third level chooser</guilabel>.</para>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Alt/Win key behavior</guilabel></term>
                <listitem><para>
                  This group of options allows you to assign the behaviour of Unix modifier keys Super, Meta, and Hyper to the <keycap>Alt</keycap> and <keycap>Windows</keycap> keys on your keyboard.
                </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>CapsLock key behavior</guilabel></term>
                <listitem><para>
                  This group has several options for the <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap> key.
                </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Compose key position</guilabel></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The Compose key allows you to combine two keypresses to make a single character. This is used to create an accented character that might not be on your keyboard layout. For example, press the Compose key, then <keycap>'</keycap>, then <keycap>e</keycap> to obtain e-acute character. </para>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Control key position</guilabel></term>
                <listitem><para>
                  Use this group of options to set the location of the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key to match the layout on older keyboards.
                </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Group Shift/Lock behavior</guilabel></term>
                <listitem><para>
                  Select keys or key combinations to switch your keyboard layout when pressed.
 
                </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Miscellaneous compatibility options</guilabel></term>
                <listitem>
                  <variablelist>
	                  <varlistentry>
	                    <term><guilabel>Shift with numpad keys works as in MS Windows.</guilabel></term>
                    	<listitem>
                    	  <para>With this option selected, using <keycap>Shift</keycap> with keys on the numerical pad when <keycap>NumLock</keycap> is off extends the current selection.</para>
                    	  <para>With this option unselected, use <keycap>Shift</keycap> with keys on the numerical pad to obtain the reverse of the current behaviour for that key. For example, when <keycap>NumLock</keycap> is off, the <keycap>8</keycap> key acts as an up-arrow. Press <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>8</keycap></keycombo> to type an '8'.</para></listitem>
                    	</varlistentry>
                    	<varlistentry><term><guilabel>Special keys (Ctrl+Alt+&lt;key&gt;) handled in a server.</guilabel></term>
	<listitem><para>Select this option to have certain keyboard shortcuts passed to the X windowing system instead of being handled by GNOME.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Third level choosers</guilabel></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A <firstterm>third level</firstterm> key allows you to obtain a third character from a key, in the same way that pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap> with a key produces a different character to pressing the key alone.</para>
                  <para>Use this group to select a key you want to act as a third level modifier key.</para>
                  <para>Pressing the third-level key and <keycap>Shift</keycap> produces a fourth character from a key.</para>
                  <para>The third and fourth level characters for your keyboard layout are shown in the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gswitchit"><application>Keyboard Indicator</application></ulink> Layout View Window.</para>
                  <!-- better link, pending CVS commit of gswitchit docs: "ghelp:gswitchit?layout-view" -->
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Use keyboard LED to show alternative group.</guilabel></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Use this option to specify that one of the light indicators on your keyboard should indicate when an alternative keyboard layout is in use.</para>
                  <note><para>The selected keyboard light will no longer indicate its standard function. For example, the Caps Lock light will not react to the <keycap>Caps Lock key</keycap>.</para></note>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="prefs-keyboard-a11y">

      <title>Billentyűzet akadálymentesítésének beállításai</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>AccessX</primary>
      <see>beállítóeszközök, Billentyűzet akadálymentesítése</see>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>billentyűzet</primary>
      <secondary>az akadálymentesítés beállításai</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>akadálymentesítés</primary>
      <secondary>a billentyűzet beállításai</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Billentyűzet akadálymentesítése</secondary>
    </indexterm>


    <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
      <anchor id="goscustaccess-6"/>
      <anchor id="goscustaccess-8"/>
      <anchor id="goscustaccess-9"/>
      <para>The <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> tabbed section allows you to set  options such as filtering out accidental keypresses and using shortcut keys without having to hold down several keys at once. These features are also known as AccessX.</para>

       <para>Ez a rész a különböző beállításokat írja le. A billentyűzet akadálymentesítésének sokkal feladatközpontúbb leírásához tekintse meg a <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-access-guide?index"><citetitle>GNOME asztali környezet akadálymentesítési kézikönyvet</citetitle></ulink>.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-85"/> lists the accessibility preferences
 that you can modify.</para>
     <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-85">
        <title>Accessibility Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
             <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>Accessibility features can be toggled with keyboard shortcuts</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                   <para>
                     Select this option to show an icon in the notification 
                     area that offers quick access to accessibility features.
                   </para>
                </entry>
             </row>
             <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>Simulate simultaneous keypresses</guilabel>
                  </para>
                  <indexterm>
                    <primary>akadálymentesítés</primary>
                    <secondary>ragadós billentyűk</secondary>
                  </indexterm>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                <para>Jelölje ki ezt a beállítást több billentyű egyidejű lenyomásának végrehajtásához a billentyűk egymás után történő lenyomásával. Ennek alternatívájaként a ragadós billentyűk engedélyezéséhez nyomja le a <keycap>Shift</keycap> billentyűt ötször egymás után.</para>
                </entry>
             </row>
             <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>Disable sticky keys if two keys are pressed together</guilabel>
                    </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                    <para>Select this option to specify that when you press two keys simultaneously,
you can no longer press keys in sequence to perform multiple simultaneous
keypresses.</para>
                </entry>
             </row>
             <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>Only accept long keypresses</guilabel>
                  </para>
                  <indexterm>
                    <primary>akadálymentesítés</primary>
                    <secondary>lassú billentyűk</secondary>
                  </indexterm>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                <para>Válassza ki ezt a beállítást azon időtartam vezérléséhez, amennyi ideig mindenképpen nyomva kell tartania egy billentyűt annak elfogadáshoz. Ennek alternatívájaként a lassú billentyűk szolgáltatás engedélyezéséhez tartsa nyomva a <keycap>Shift</keycap> billentyűt nyolc másodpercig.</para>
                </entry>
             </row>
             <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>Késleltetés</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>Use the slider
to specify the period of time that you must press-and-hold
a key before acceptance.</para>
                </entry>
             </row>
             <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>Ignore fast duplicate keypresses</guilabel>
                  </para>
                  <indexterm>
                    <primary>akadálymentesítés</primary>
                    <secondary>billentyűszűrés</secondary>
                  </indexterm>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to accept a key input and to control the key repeat characteristics
of the keyboard.</para>
                </entry>
             </row>
             <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>Késleltetés</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                   <para>Use the slider to specify the interval to wait after the first
keypress before the automatic repeat of a pressed key.</para>
                </entry>
             </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Beállítások kipróbálása</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>A tesztterület egy interaktív felület, ahol láthatja, hogy a billentyűzet beállításai hogyan hatnak gépeléskor a megjelenítésre. Gépeljen a tesztterületre a beállítások hatásainak teszteléséhez.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>To configure audio feedback for keyboard accessibility features,
      click the <guibutton>Audio Feedback</guibutton> button. It opens the
      <guilabel>Keyboard Accessibility Audio Feedback</guilabel> window.</para>
    </sect3>

   <sect3>
      <title>Keyboard Accessibility Audio Feedback</title>
      <para>Configure audio feedback for keyboard accessibility features.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-86"/> lists the audio feedback preferences
      that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-86">
        <title>Audio Feedback Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Beep when accessibility features are turned on or off</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Jelölje ki ezt a beállítást, ha hangjelzést akar hallani egy szolgáltatás, például a ragadós billentyűk vagy lassú billentyűk engedélyezésekor vagy letiltásakor.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>
                   <guilabel>Beep when a toggle key is pressed</guilabel>
                 </para>
                 <indexterm>
                    <primary>akadálymentesítés</primary>
                    <secondary>váltóbillentyűk</secondary>
                  </indexterm>
              </entry>
	      <entry valign="top">
                 <para>Válassza ki ezt a beállítást a hangjelzéshez váltóbillentyű lenyomásakor. Egy csipogást fog hallani a váltóbillentyűk engedélyezésekor. Két csipogást fog hallani a váltóbillentyűk letiltásakor.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>
                   <guilabel>Beep when a modifier key is pressed</guilabel>
                 </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>Select this option for an audible indication when you 
                 press a modifier key.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>
                   <guilabel>Beep when a key is pressed</guilabel>
                 </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>Select this option for an audible indication when  
                 a key is pressed.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>
                   <guilabel>Beep when a key is accepted</guilabel>
                 </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>Select this option for an audible indication when  
                 a key is accepted.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>
                   <guilabel>Beep when a key is rejected</guilabel>
                 </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                 <para>Select this option for an audible indication when  
                 a key is rejected.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
   </sect3>
 
   <sect3>
     <title>Mouse Keys Preferences</title>
     <anchor id="goscustaccess-10"/>
     <para>The options in the <guilabel>Mouse Keys</guilabel> tabbed section
     let you configure the keyboard as a substitute for the mouse.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-88"/> lists the mouse keys preferences
 that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-88">
        <title>Typing Break Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Pointer can be controlled using the keypad</guilabel>
                </para>
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>akadálymentesítés</primary>
                  <secondary>egérbillentyűk</secondary>
                </indexterm>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
               <para>Válassza ki ezt a beállítást az egér emulálásához a numerikus billentyűzettel. A billentyűk felsorolása, és az azzal egyenértékű funkciók megtekinthetők a <citetitle>GNOME asztali környezet akadálymentesítési kézikönyvben</citetitle>, azon belül a <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-access-guide?dtconfig-14"><citetitle>Az az egér emulálásának engedélyezése a billentyűzetnek</citetitle> alfejezetben.</ulink></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                   <guilabel>Gyorsítás</guilabel> 
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Use the slider to specify how long it takes the pointer to accelerate to maximum speed.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                   <guilabel>Sebesség</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Use the slider
to specify the maximum speed that the pointer moves across
the screen.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Késleltetés</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Use the slider to specify the period of time that must pass
after a keypress before the pointer moves.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
  </sect3>

    <sect3 id="goscustdesk-86">
      <title>Typing Break Preferences</title>
      <para>Configure the Typing Break Preferences to make GNOME remind you to rest after you have been using the keyboard and mouse for a long time. During a Typing Break, the screen will be locked.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-87"/> lists the typing break preferences
 that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-87">
        <title>Typing Break Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Lock screen to enforce typing break</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to
lock the screen when you are due a typing break.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Work interval lasts</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Use the spin box to specify how long you can work
before a typing break occurs.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Break interval lasts</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Use the spin box to specify the length of your typing
breaks.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Allow postponing of breaks</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Select this option if you want to be able to postpone
typing breaks.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <note><para>
        If you stop using the keyboard and mouse for a length of time equal to the <guilabel>Break interval</guilabel> setting, the current work interval will be reset.
      </para></note>
    </sect3>    
    
    
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="prefs-mouse">
    <title>Egér beállításai</title>
    <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
    <anchor id="goscustperiph-5"/>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Egér</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>egér</primary>
      <secondary>beállítás</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>With the <application>Mouse</application> preference tool
    you can:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>configure your mouse for right-hand use or for left-hand use,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>      
        <para>specify the speed and sensitivity of mouse movement,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>configure mouse accessibility features.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    
    <sect3 id="goscustdesk-55">
      <title>General Mouse Preferences</title>
      <para>Use the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tabbed section to specify whether
      the mouse buttons are configured for left-hand or right-hand use and configure
      the speed and sensitivity of your mouse.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustperiph-TBL-6"/> lists the general mouse preferences
that you can modify.</para>

    <!-- convert to variablelist -->
    <table frame="topbot" id="goscustperiph-TBL-6">
        <title>Mouse Button Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="colspec18" colwidth="19.21*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec19" colwidth="46.79*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Right-handed</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to configure your mouse for right-hand use. When you configure your mouse for right-hand use, the left mouse button is the primary button and the right mouse button is the secondary button.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Left-handed</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Jelölje be ezt a négyzetet, ha az egeret a balkezes használathoz szeretné beállítani. A balkezes használatra beállított egér jobb és bal egérgombjainak szerepe felcserélődik.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Show position of pointer when the Control key is pressed</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to enable a mouse pointer animation
when you press and release the Control key. This feature can assist
you to locate the mouse pointer.</para>
                <note>
                  <para>The position of the Control key on the keyboard can be 
                  modified in the Keyboard Layout Options dialog, see 
                  <xref linkend="prefs-keyboard-layoutoptions"/>.</para>
                </note>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Gyorsítás</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>A csúszka segítségével állítsa be az egérmutató sebességét.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Érzékenység</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>A csúszka segítségével állítsa be az egérmutató egérmozgással szembeni érzékenységét.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Küszöbszint</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>A csúszka segítségével állítsa be azt a távolságot, amennyire el kell mozdítani ahhoz egy elemet, hogy a művelet húzás és ejtés műveletnek számítson.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Timeout</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>A csúszka használatával beállíthatja a kattintások között eltelt időt a dupla kattintáshoz. Ha az itt megadott időköznél több telik el két kattintás között, a rendszer nem fogja dupla kattintásnak értelmezni a műveletet.</para>

                <para>Use the light bulb icon to check double-click sensitivity: the light will light up briefly for a click, but stay lit for a double-click.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="goscustdesk-53">
      <title>Mouse Accessibility Preferences</title>
      <para>Use the <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> tabbed section to configure
      accessibility features that can help people who have difficulty with exact positioning of the pointer or with pressing the mouse buttons:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
              Open a contextual menu by clicking and holding the primary mouse button; this is useful for users that can manipulate only one button.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
              Perform different types of mouse button click by software; this useful for users that are not able to manipulate any buttons. The types of click that can be performed are:
               <variablelist>
                 <varlistentry>
                   <term>Single click</term>
                   <listitem>
                     <para>
                       A single click of the primary mouse button
                     </para>
                   </listitem>
                 </varlistentry>
                 <varlistentry>
                   <term>Double click</term>
                   <listitem>
                     <para>
                        A double click of the primary mouse button
                     </para>
                   </listitem>
                 </varlistentry>
                 <varlistentry>
                   <term>Drag click</term>
                   <listitem>
                     <para>
                       A click that begins a drag operation
                     </para>
                   </listitem>
                 </varlistentry>
                 <varlistentry>
                   <term>Secondary click</term>
                   <listitem>
                     <para>
                       A single click of the secondary mouse button
                     </para>
                   </listitem>
                 </varlistentry>
               </variablelist>
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-47"/> lists the mouse accessibility preferences
that you can modify:</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-47">
        <title>Mouse Motion Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="30.10*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="69.90*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Trigger secondary click by holding down the primary button</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to enable simulated secondary clicks by pressing the primary mouse button for an extended time.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Delay</guilabel> slider in the <guilabel>Simulated Secondary Click</guilabel> section
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Use the slider to specify how long the primary button must be pressed to simulate a secondary click.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Initiate click when stopping pointer movement</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to enable automatic clicks when the mouse stops. Use the additional preferences in the <guilabel>Dwell Click</guilabel> section to configure how the type of click is chosen.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Delay</guilabel> slider in the <guilabel>Dwell Click</guilabel> section
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Use the slider to specify how long the pointer must remain at rest before an automatic click will be triggered.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Motion threshold</guilabel> slider 
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Use the slider to specify how much the pointer may move to still be considered at rest.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Choose type of click beforehand</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to pick the type of click to perform 
                from a window or panel applet.</para> 
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Show click type window</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  When this option is enabled, the different types of click (single click, double click, drag click or secondary click) can be selected in a window.</para> 
                <note><para>The <guilabel>Dwell Click</guilabel> panel applet can
                be used instead of the window.</para></note>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Choose type of click with mouse gestures</guilabel> 
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Select this option to pick the type of click by moving the mouse in a certain direction. The four combo boxes below this option allow to assign directions to the different types of click. Note that each direction can be used only for one type of click.</para> 
              
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Single click</guilabel> 
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  Choose the direction to trigger a single click.
                </para> 
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Dpuble click</guilabel> 
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  Choose the direction to trigger a double click.
                </para> 
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Drag click</guilabel> 
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  Choose the direction to trigger a drag click.
                </para> 
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Secondary click</guilabel> 
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry rowsep="0" colsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  Choose the direction to trigger a secondary click.
                </para> 
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="goscustdesk-70">
    <title>Display Preferences</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Display</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Use the <application>Display</application>
preference tool to configure the monitors that your computer uses.</para>
<note><para>On most laptop keyboards, you can use the key combination
<keycombo><keycap>Fn</keycap><keycap>F7</keycap></keycombo> to cycle between
several typical monitor configurations without starting the <application>Display</application> preference tool.
</para></note>
<para>You can drag and move the graphical representations of the monitors in
the upper part of the window to arrange how they are connected to form your
desktop area. Note that the application displays small 'stickers' in the top
left corner of each monitor to help you identify which rectangle corresponds
to which monitor.</para>
<note><para>In contrast to most other preference tools, changes you make in
the <application>Display</application> preference tool don't take effect until
you click the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button, and will revert to their
previous settings unless you confirm the changes. This is a precaution to
prevent bad display settings from rendering your computer unusable.</para></note>
<para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-72"/> lists the display preferences that
you can modify for the currently selected monitor. The currently selected
monitor is the one whose graphical representation has a bold black outline.
It is also indicated by the background color of the section label.
              </para>
    <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-72">
      <title>Display Preferences</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
        <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
        <thead>
          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry>
              <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Leírás</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Mirror Screens</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Select this option to have all monitors show the whole desktop.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                 <guibutton>Detect Monitors</guibutton>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
               <para>Use this button to make your desktop notice newly plugged
                 in or unplugged monitors. This is necessary, since it would
                 cost too much energy to constantly check for these changes.
               </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Resolution</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Select the resolution to use for the currently selected
                monitor from the drop-down list. <emphasis>Resolution</emphasis>
                refers to the pixel dimensions of the screen. A larger
                resolution means that more things fit on the screen, but
                everything will be smaller.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Refresh rate</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Select the refresh rate to use for the currently
                selected monitor from the drop-down list. The <emphasis>refresh
                rate</emphasis> determines how often the computer redraws the
                screen. A too low refresh rate (below 60) makes the monitor
                flicker and can cause discomfort to your eyes. This is less
                of a problem on lcd displays.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Rotation</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Select the rotation for the currently selected monitor. This option may not be supported on all graphics cards.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <guilabel>Show displays in panel</guilabel>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Select this option to show an icon in the notification area
                that allows you to quickly change the rotation.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="goscustmulti-2">
    <title>Hangok beállításai</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Hang</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>hang</primary>
      <secondary>beállítások</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>hang</primary>
      <secondary>események hangjai</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>hang hozzárendelése eseményhez</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>volume</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The <application>Sound</application> preference tool enables
you to control devices and volume for sound input and output. 
You can also specify which sounds to play when particular events occur.</para>
    <para>A <application>Hang</application> beállítóeszközben a következő lehetőségei vannak:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Hangesemények</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Input</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Output</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>You can change the overall output volume using the <guilabel>Output volume</guilabel> slider at the top of the window. The <guilabel>Mute</guilabel> checkbox allows to temporarily suppress all output without disturbing the current volume.</para>
    <sect3 id="goscustdesk-48">
      <title>Sound Effects Preferences</title>
      <para>A sound theme is collection of sound effects that are associated to various events, such as opening a dialog, clicking a button or selecting an item in a menu. One of the most prominent event sounds is the <emphasis>System Bell</emphasis> sound that often played to indicate a keyboard input error. Use the <guilabel>Sound Effects</guilabel> tabbed section of the <application>Sound</application> preference tool to choose a sound theme and modify the bell sound.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustmulti-TBL-6"/> lists the sound effects preferences
that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustmulti-TBL-6">
        <title>Sound Effects Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="colspec18" colwidth="19.21*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec19" colwidth="46.79*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para><guilabel>Alert Volume</guilabel> slider</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Use the <guilabel>Alert Volume</guilabel> slider to
control the volume for event sounds.</para>
                <para>The <guilabel>Mute</guilabel> checkbox allows to
                temporarily suppress event sounds without modifying the
                current volume.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Sound Theme </guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Use this combobox to select a different sound theme.</para>
                <para>Choose <guilabel>No sounds</guilabel> to turn off all event sounds.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para><guilabel>Choose an alert sound </guilabel> list</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Choose an alternative sound for the System Bell from 
                this list.</para>
                <para>Selecting a list element plays the sound.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para><guilabel>Enable window and button sounds </guilabel> checkbox</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Uncheck this option if you don't want to hear sounds
                for window-related events (such as a dialog or a menu appearing)
                and button clicks.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Sound Input Preferences</title>
      <para>Use the <guilabel>Input</guilabel> tabbed section to set your 
      preferences for sound input.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-1"/> lists the
sound input preferences that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-1">
        <title>Sound Input Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="colspec18" colwidth="19.21*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec19" colwidth="46.79*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Input volume </guilabel> slider
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>Use the input volume slider to control the input level.</para>
                <para>The <guilabel>Mute </guilabel> checkbox allows to temporarily suppress all input without disturbing the current input level.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Input level</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>The <guilabel>Input level</guilabel> display provides
                visual feedback that helps to select a suitable input volume.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Choose a device for sound input </guilabel> list
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>Choose the device that you want to receive sound input
                from.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <note><para>Note that the input volume can also be controlled with
      the microphone icon that is shown in the notification area of the panel
      when an application is listening for sound input.</para></note>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Sound Output Preferences</title>
      <para>Use the <guilabel>Output</guilabel> tabbed section to set your 
      preferences for sound output.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustdesk-TBL-2"/> lists the
sound output preferences that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustdesk-TBL-2">
        <title>Sound Output Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="colspec18" colwidth="19.21*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec19" colwidth="46.79*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Output volume </guilabel> slider
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>Use the output volume slider to control the overall output volume.</para>
                <para>The <guilabel>Mute </guilabel> checkbox allows to temporarily suppress all output without disturbing the current volume.</para>
                <para>Note that the <guilabel>Output volume</guilabel> slider 
                is located above the tabbed section at the top of the window.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Choose a device for sound output </guilabel> list
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>Choose the device that you want to hear sound output
                from.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec18" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Balance </guilabel> slider
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec19" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <para>Use the <guilabel>Balance</guilabel> slider to control
                the left/right balance of an output device that has more than
                one channel (e.g. stereo or 5.1).</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <note><para>Note that the output volume can also be controlled with
      the speaker icon that is shown in the notification area of the panel.</para></note>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="goscustdesk-41">
      <title>Application Sound Preferences</title>
      <para>Use the <guilabel>Applications</guilabel> tabbed section to 
      control the volume of sound played by individual applications.</para>
      <para>Each application that is currently playing sound is identified
      by its name and icon.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

<!--
<sect2 id="goscustdesk-79">
<title>Customizing PalmOS Devices</title>
<indexterm><primary>preference tools</primary><secondary>PalmOS devices</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Information to be supplied in a future release.</para>
</sect2>
-->


</sect1>


<sect1 id="prefs-system">
	<title>Rendszer</title>


  <sect2 id="prefs-multimedia">
    <title>Multimedia Systems Selector</title>
    <para>See the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gstreamer-properties">GStreamer Properties Manual</ulink>.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="prefs-sessions">
    <title>Sessions Preferences</title>
    
    <!-- preserve for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="goscustsession-5"/>   
        
    <indexterm>
      <primary>beállítóeszközök</primary>
      <secondary>Munkamenetek</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>munkamenetek</primary>
      <secondary>beállítások</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>automatikusan elinduló programok</primary>
      <secondary>személyre szabás</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The <application>Sessions</application>
preference tool enables you to manage your sessions. You can set session preferences,
and specify which applications to start when you start a session. You can
configure sessions to save the state of applications in the GNOME Desktop,
and to restore the state when you start another session. You can also use
this preference tool to manage multiple GNOME sessions.</para>
    <para>You can customize the settings for sessions and startup applications
in the following functional areas:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Session Options</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Startup Programs</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <sect3 id="goscustsession-16">
      <title>Setting Session Preferences</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>munkamenetek</primary>
        <secondary>setting options</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>Use the <guilabel>Session Options</guilabel> tabbed section
to manage multiple sessions, and to set preferences for the current session.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustsession-TBL-11"/> lists the session options that
you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustsession-TBL-11">
        <title>Session Options</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="18.86*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="47.14*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Automatically remember running applications when logging out</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>automatikusan elinduló programok</primary>
                  <secondary>munkamenetkezelt</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Select this
option if you want the session manager to save the state of your session 
when logging out. The session manager saves the session-managed applications 
that are open, and the settings associated with the session-managed applications 
when you log out. The next time that you start a session, the applications start 
automatically, with the saved settings.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Remember currently running applications</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>automatikusan elinduló programok</primary>
                  <secondary>munkamenetkezelt</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Select this
option if you want the session manager to save the current state of your session.
The session manager saves the session-managed applications that are open,
and the settings associated with the session-managed applications. The next
time that you start a session, the applications start automatically, with
the saved settings.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="goscustsession-12">
      <title>Configuring Startup Applications</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>automatikusan elinduló programok</primary>
        <secondary>nem munkamenetkezelt</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>Use the <guilabel>Startup Programs</guilabel>
tabbed section of the <application>Sessions</application> preference tool
to specify non-session-managed <firstterm>startup applications</firstterm>.
Startup applications are applications that start automatically when you start
a session. You specify the commands that run the non-session-managed applications
in the <guilabel>Startup Programs</guilabel> tabbed section. The commands
execute automatically when you log in.</para>
      <para>You can also start session-managed applications automatically. For more
information, see <xref linkend="goscustsession-16"/>.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="goscustsession-TBL-19"/> lists the startup applications
preferences that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" id="goscustsession-TBL-19">
        <title>Startup Programs Preferences</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="col1" colwidth="18.86*"/>
          <colspec colname="col2" colwidth="47.14*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1" colsep="0">
                <para>Párbeszédablak-elem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="col2" colsep="0">
                <para>Leírás</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <guilabel> Additional startup programs</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="col2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">
                <para>Use this table to manage non-session-managed
startup applications as follows:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>To add a startup application, click on the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>New Startup Program</guilabel> dialog is displayed. Enter the name of the appplication in the <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field. Then enter the command to start the application in the <guilabel>Command</guilabel> field. you can also specify a comment in the <guilabel>Comment</guilabel> field</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>To edit a startup application, select the startup application,
then click on the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Edit Startup
Program</guilabel> dialog is displayed. Use the dialog to modify the command
and the startup order for the startup application.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>To delete a startup application, select the startup application,
then click on the <guilabel>Remove</guilabel> button.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

</sect1>


</chapter>
