<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop">
	<title>Fedora Desktop</title>
	<remark>This beat is located here: <ulink type="http" url="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Docs/Beats/Desktop">https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Docs/Beats/Desktop</ulink></remark>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-Spanning_Desktop">
		<title>Spanning Desktop</title>
		<para>
			In the latest version of '''Xorg''' included in this release, if you have a dual monitor setup, your desktop display will span across them instead of using a cloned display by default. This matches the behaviour of other operating systems. 
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-Webcam">
		<title>Better webcam support</title>

		<para>
			The better webcam support feature for Fedora&nbsp;10 did much to improve webcam support in Linux. We now have a library (<application>libv4l</application>) for decompressing various proprietary video formats in user space, and almost all applications that use webcams have been patched to use this library.
		</para>

		<para>Fedora&nbsp;12 contains a second push for better webcam support, comprising three pieces:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Lots of testing, fixing bugs, and improving of existing in-kernel drivers.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Add video processing to <application>libv4l</application> for better video quality for cams which lack any of the following in hardware:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>White balancing</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Gamma correction</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Automatic adjustment of exposure (gain)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recognize laptop cams which are known to be installed upside down and rotate the image 180 degrees in software</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Clean up existing out-of-tree drivers, moving the decompression to <application>libv4l</application> where needed and merge them into the mainline, specifically the following ones:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>qc-usb: stv0600 (and similar)-based cams, mainly Logitech QuickCam Express (done as of kernel 2.6.29)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ov51x-jpeg: ov511(+) and ov518(+) driver (done as of kernel 2.6.31rc1, libv4l-0.6.0)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>qc-usb-messenger: st6422-based cams mainly Logitech QuickCam Messenger models (done as of kernel 2.6.31rc1)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>sn9c20x: sn9c20x-based cams, many newer cheap cams (done as of kernel 2.6.31rc2)</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-ABRT">
		<title>ABRT</title>
		<para>
		  <indexterm>
		    <primary>ABRT</primary>
		  </indexterm>
		The <application>ABRT</application> automatic bug reporting tool replaces <application>bug-buddy</application> and <application>kerneloops</application> in the Fedora&nbsp;12 desktop. <application>ABRT</application> has an extensible architecture and can not only catch and report segmentation faults and kernel oops, but also python backtraces. In contrast to <application>bug-buddy</application>, it can catch segmentation faults in any binary, not just GTK+ applications.</para>

		<para>If you have manually modified the <application>GConf</application> settings for the <application>bug-buddy</application> GTK+ module before, you may see warning messages like the following from GTK+ applications:</para>

<screen><computeroutput>Gtk-Message: Failed to load module "gnomebreakpad":</computeroutput>
<computeroutput>libgnomebreakpad.so: cannot open shared object file: No such file or directory</computeroutput></screen>


		<para>To stop these messages, run the following command in a terminal in your session:</para>

<screen><command>gconftool-2 --type bool --set /apps/gnome_settings_daemon/gtk-modules/gnomebreakpad false</command></screen>


	</section>

	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME">
		<title>GNOME 2.28</title>
		<para>
		  <indexterm>
		    <primary>GNOME</primary>
		  </indexterm>

			The <application>GNOME 2.28.1</application> desktop is part of this release, and is the default environment used in the Fedora Desktop Live image. The Desktop Live image is a downloadable CD you can use to test the new GNOME environment with or without installing it. The image can be written to CD, or to a USB flash disk; for instructions, refer to <ulink url="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/FedoraLiveCD/USBHowTo"></ulink>.
		</para>
		<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME-Icons">
			<title>Icons in menus and buttons</title>
			<para>
				Icons in menus and buttons are not shown by default in <application>GNOME 2.28</application>. To get the old, icon-rich appearance back, select <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Appearance</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, click the <guilabel>Interface</guilabel> tab and enable <guilabel>Show icons in menus</guilabel>. There is, however, no menu interface to enable the icons for the buttons. To set the corresponding GConf keys instead for enabling both the menus and buttons to have icons:
<screen><command>gconftool-2 --type boolean --set /desktop/gnome/interface/buttons_have_icons true</command>
<command>gconftool-2 --type boolean --set /desktop/gnome/interface/menus_have_icons true</command></screen>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME-Changes">
		  <title>Additional imrpovements in GNOME 2.28</title>
		<para>
		  Compared to previous Fedora releases, there are a
		  number of other changes in the default configuration
		  of the GNOME desktop:
		  <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem><para> The 'Windows' preference dialog
		    is no longer installed by default. It is still
		    available in the control-center-extra package
		    </para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para> The 'Main Menu' preference dialog
		    is no longer installed by default. It is still
		    available in the alacarte package
		    </para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para> The user switcher has been moved
		    to the far right of the top panel
		    </para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para> The 'Show Desktop' button has
		    been removed by default. If you prefer, you can
		    add this panel applet back with right click, "Add
		    to Panel..." and selecting "Show Desktop".
		    </para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para> The number of workspaces in the
		    'Workspace Switcher' has been reduced to 2
		    </para></listitem>
		    <listitem><para> The panel now adds padding
		    between applets and between icons in the
		    notification area. The padding can be removed with
		    the following commands:
		    <screen>
gconftool-2 --type int --set /apps/panel/toplevels/top_panel/padding 0
gconftool-2 --type int --set /apps/panel/toplevels/bottom_panel/padding 0
gconftool-2 --type int --set /apps/panel/applets/systray/prefs/padding 0
		    </screen>
		    </para></listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		</para>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME-Gnote">
		<title>Gnote</title>
			<para>
			  <indexterm>
			    <primary>gnote</primary>
			  </indexterm>
			  <indexterm>
			    <primary>tomboy</primary>
			  </indexterm>
				<application>Gnote</application> is installed by default in GNOME for this release replacing <application>Tomboy</application>. <application>Gnote</application> is a port of <application>Tomboy</application> from Mono to C++ and consumes fewer resources. <application>Gnote</application> is both an applet that can sit in your GNOME panel as well as a individual application you can run within other desktop environments. Fedora Desktop Live CD since the Fedora 10 release has excluded Mono and hence Mono-based applications like <application>Tomboy</application> due to lack of space. <application>Gnote</application> will be installed by default in the Live CD as well in this release. <application>Tomboy</application> is still available as a optional alternative. If you are upgrading from the previous release you will not be migrated to <application>Gnote</application> and will continue to have <application>Tomboy</application>. <application>Tomboy</application> users can migrate easily to <application>Gnote</application> as it shares the file format and a plugin is available in <application>Gnote</application> that will automatically import <application>Tomboy</application> notes on first run. Many of the <application>Tomboy</application> plugins have been ported to <application>Gnote</application>. The following plugins are available as part of <application>Gnote</application>:
				
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Bugzilla Links</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Tomboy Importer</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Fixed Width</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Insert Timestamp</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Export to HTML</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Printing Support</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Sticky Notes Importer</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Backlinks</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can copy the notes from <application>Tomboy</application> to <application>Gnote</application> using the following command in your home directory:
<screen><command>cp -r .tomboy .gnote</command></screen>
			</para>
			<para>
				The sticky notes applet is not provided anymore since <application>Gnote</application> provides a better note taking utility and is available by default in this release.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME-Sound_preferences">
			<title>Sound preferences</title>
			<para>
				The GNOME sound preferences now supports profile switching.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME-Empathy">
			<title>Empathy</title>
			<para>
			  <indexterm>
			    <primary>empathy</primary>
			  </indexterm>
			  <indexterm>
			    <primary>pidgin</primary>
			  </indexterm>

				<application>Empathy</application> replaces <application>Pidgin</application> as the default instant messenger in GNOME. <application>Empathy</application> is better integrated with GNOME and provides audio and video functionality for users of the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP, formerly Jabber) with more improvements planned. <application>Empathy</application> supports importing accounts from <application>Pidgin</application> on first run so you can migrate more easily. If you are upgrading from a previous release, you will continue to have <application>Pidgin</application> by default. <application>Pidgin</application> continues to be available in the repository and is actively maintained.
			</para>

			<para>The major advantages and disadvantages of <application>Empathy</application> are:
				<itemizedlist>
					<title>Advantages</title>
					<listitem><para>Better GNOME integration. Passwords are stored in the keyring instead of plain text like in <application>Pidgin</application></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Voice chat with <application>GoogleTalk</application>. Voice chat requires extra <application>gstreamer</application> codecs and manual firewall reconfiguration and <application>Pidgin</application> now uses the same framework as well.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Account migration support from <application>Pidgin</application> has been added to <application>Empathy</application>.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Support for collaboration with <application>Abiword</application> and other programs</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Geo Location (very recent feature) </para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<itemizedlist>
					<title>Disdvantages</title>
					<listitem><para>Missing plugin system, so many of the add-on features available to <application>Pidgin</application> (like encryption) are not available to <application>Empathy</application></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>No proxy support </para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME-Totem">
			<title>Totem</title>
			<para>
			  <indexterm>
			    <primary>totem</primary>
			  </indexterm>
			  <indexterm>
			    <primary>gstreamer</primary>
			  </indexterm>
				<application>Totem</application> only supports a <application>gstreamer</application> back end now. The <application>totem-xine</application> back end has been removed completely.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME-Epiphany">
			<title>Epiphany</title>
			<para>
			  <indexterm>
			    <primary>epiphany</primary>
			  </indexterm>
				<application>Epiphany</application> in this release is now using the WebKit engine instead of the Gecko engine from <application>Firefox</application>.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-GNOME_Shell">
			<title>GNOME Shell &mdash; preview of GNOME 3</title>
			<para>
			  <indexterm>
			    <primary>GNOME shell</primary>
			  </indexterm>
				A very early version of GNOME Shell is now available in the repository. GNOME Shell is a key part of GNOME 3 and is in active development with the heavy involvement of Fedora developers and interaction designers. A simple way to try out GNOME Shell is to install the <package>desktop-effects</package> package:
<screen><command>yum install desktop-effects gnome-shell</command></screen>
			</para>
			<para>
				Then, click <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Desktop Effects</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
			</para>
			<para>
				If you would like to configure it manually, run
<screen><command>mkdir ~/.config/autostart</command>
<command>ln -s /usr/share/applications/gnome-shell.desktop ~/.config/autostart</command></screen>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can also run the following to invoke it directly.
<screen><command>gnome-shell --replace &amp;</command></screen>
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-KDE">
		<title>KDE 4.3</title>
		<para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>KDE</primary>
	    </indexterm>
			<application>KDE 4.3</application> is part of this release and is the default environment in the Fedora KDE Desktop Live image. The KDE Desktop Live image is a downloadable CD you can use to test the new KDE environment with or without installing it. You can write the image to a CD or to a USB flash drive.
		</para>
		<para>
			<application>KDE 4.3</application> is the latest release of KDE 4, with many enhancements and new features. <application>Plasma</application> has a new <citetitle>Air</citetitle> look, improved job and notification management and fully-configurable keyboard shortcuts. There are also new <application>Plasma</application> widgets and existing ones are improved. <application>KWin</application> is optimized for performance and brings new desktop effects to KDE. KDE now contains a new bug reporting tool, making it easier to report bugs to the KDE developers.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Fedora_Desktop-moblin">
	  <title>Moblin Desktop</title>
	  <para>
	    <indexterm>
	      <primary>moblin-desktop</primary>
	    </indexterm>
	    The Moblin Architecture is designed to support multiple
	    platforms and usage models ranging from Netbooks and
	    NetTops to Mobile Internet Devices (MID) and various
	    embedded usage models, such as In Vehicle Infotainment
	    systems.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    A preview of the Core Moblin 2 desktop environment for
	    NetBook/NetTop/MID devices is available for testing in
	    Fedora.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    The Moblin Desktop may be installed as a group with yum:
	    <screen>
sudo yum install @moblin-desktop
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</section>

</section>


