<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Electronic_Design_Automation">
  <title>Electronic Design Automation</title> <remark>This beat is
  located here: <ulink type="http"
  url="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Documentation_EDA_Beat">https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Documentation_EDA_Beat</ulink></remark>
  <para>
    <indexterm><primary>Electronic Design
    Automation</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>Fedora
    Electronic Lab</primary></indexterm> This section outlines changes
    in the Fedora Electronic Lab for Fedora 12.  Note that a number of
    the applications in FEL have application to a number of
    communities. These specific applications are outlined in the
    Circuit Design (which includes simulation and PCB layout) and
    Embedded Development sections of these notes.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Collaborative Code Review</title>
    <para>
      <indexterm><primary>Collaborative Code Review</primary></indexterm>
      One of the many faces of digital hardware design entails
      tracking many files to be fed to multiple EDA tools. The
      eventual reports or netlists are carefully analysed and logged
      as part of the sign-off methodology. Each company tracks these
      project dependent files under a certain directory structure and
      under a certain revision controlled system of their choice.
    </para>
    <para>
      We have included an efficient and reliable code review solution
      into the Fedora collection. This trac-based peerreview solution
      will also help create links and seamless references between
      bugs, tasks, changesets and files. Project coordinators will
      have a more realistic the overview of the on-going project and
      track the progress very easy with respect to different
      milestones and deadlines.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Eclipse Default IDE</title>
    <para>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Eclipse Default IDE</primary>
	<secondary>Electronic Design Automation</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      With the help and support from Fedora Eclipse team, Eclipse
      becomes FEL’s prime IDE for HDL IP development and
      documentation. This adoption is to maintain true
      interoperability between tools offered by different embedded
      software vendors.
    </para>
    <para>
      The following plugins provided by default on the Fedora
      Electronic Lab platform will enhance :
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    frontend design
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    autogeneration of documentation and maintenance of
	    professional datasheets
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Perl/Tcl scripting (Perl modules which featured as from FEL10)
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    version controlled projects
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table frame="all" id="tbl-FEL-Eclipse-Plugins">
	<title>Eclipse Plugins selected for hardware design</title>
	<indexterm><primary>eclipse-veditor</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>eclipse-eclox</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>eclipse-texlipse</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>eclipse-cdt</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>eclipse-dltk-tcl</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>eclipse-epic</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>eclipse-subclipse</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>eclipse-egit</primary></indexterm>
	<tgroup cols="2">
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Package
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Description
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		eclipse-veditor
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Helps digital IC designers/FPGA designers develop
		Verilog/ VHDL code on Eclipse.  Provides a realtime
		error and warnings notification of typos, missing
		signals, unnecessary signals etc.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		eclipse-eclox
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		If the vhdl code entails doxygen style comments, a
		pdf can be autogenerated and used either during
		internal meetings or sent to the client.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		eclipse-texlipse
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Since the pdf is generated from latex, the texlipse
		plugin will provide some additional page layout
		formatting and easy pdf creation. The pdf creation
		is now only Ctrl-S, rather than a manual click like
		one would do on kile. That said, kile will be
		removed from the FEL livedvd.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		eclipse-cdt
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Provides Embedded C and C++ development tools.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		eclipse-dltk-tcl
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Tcl scripts can be maintained along side with the
		HDL code.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		eclipse-epic
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Perl scripts can be maintained along side with the
		HDL code.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		eclipse-subclipse
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Adds Subversion integration to the Eclipse IDE
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		eclipse-egit
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Adds distributed version controlled GIT integration
		to the Eclipse IDE
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Analog ASIC Design</title>

    <variablelist>
      
      <varlistentry>
	<term>toped</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>toped</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    Updated to the consolidation release 0.9.4. The Fedora
	    Toped package sets the variable $TPD_GLOBAL to
	    /usr/share/toped by default so that the user could run
	    toped out of the box.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Graham Petley and Krustev Svilen provided 2 TELL files
	    as a demonstration how toped can interact with Pharosc
	    Standard Cells via toped’s GDSII and CIF parsers.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Highlights
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  New graphic renderer which speeds-up the drawing
		  up-to 3.5 times. Requires openGL version 1.4 (F-11
		  uses 1.3, but this is not an issue) and Virtual
		  Buffer Objects. It will be used as a base for future
		  graphical effects.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The old renderer remains to cover graphic drivers
		  implementing older openGL versions and particularly
		  virtual desktops.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The speed is also improved significantly.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Updates and fixes in the external interfaces. GDSII
		  in particular.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  New utility for conversion of Virtuoso(C) technology
		  files to TELL.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  TDT format updated with new records. Version updated
		  to 0.7.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  TDT format updated with new records. Version updated
		  to 0.7.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Further updates on the user interface customization
		  - toolbars.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Updates in the internal handling of the cell
		  references. In result layer 0 is handled as a normal
		  layer now.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	  <warning>
	    <title>
	      Old Toped releases will not be able to read TDT files
	      produced by this release.
	    </title>
	    <para>
	      There is a certain amount of code which is not yet
	      merged to the main development trunk, including the
	      calibre error report parser. The suggestion is to do
	      that after the release. Some features were postponed
	      instead of sacrificing stability at this stage.
	    </para>
	  </warning>

	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Magic</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>magic</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>magic-doc</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    Fedora Magic has been updated to 8.0.54.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Fedora Magic package has its documentation on a separate
	    package called : <package>magic-doc</package>. The latter
	    includes some examples of scmos and tutorials. Advanced
	    Magic VLSI users would also be interested in reading the
	    documentation again to grasp the fine details entailed in
	    the 8.0 series.
	  </para>
	  <para>Features:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  outline vector fonts (courtesy of the freefont
		  project), and aims to clean up a lot of problems
		  associated with labels in Magic.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  All the display, manipulation, OpenGL are complete.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Features some "cifoutput" operators for use with the
		  new "cif paint" command, for manipulating layout
		  using boolean operators.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Runtime speed has been improved.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Two additional menus have been added for grid
		  manipulation and text settings.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Electric</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>electric</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    <package>electric</package> has been updated to 8.09.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Please note that because most of the electric userbase use
	    third party plugins that due to the licensing
	    incompatibilities wih Fedora, FEL can not add those
	    plugins. That said, Fedora Electronic Lab team understands
	    that releasing a new upstream version would break
	    interoperability with the user’s plugins.  Hence new
	    versions of electric will once make their way to the
	    updates-testing repository.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Digital Design</title>

    <variablelist>
      
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Dinotrace</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>dinotrace</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    New to Fedora &PRODVER;,Dinotrace is a waveform viewer
	    which understands Verilog Value Change Dumps, ASCII, and
	    other trace formats.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    It allows placing cursors, highlighting signals,
	    searching, printing, and other capabilities superior to
	    many commercial waveform viewers.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Dinotrace is optimized for rapid debugging. With VTRACE, a
	    simulation failure will automatically place cursors where
	    errors occur, add comments visible in the wave form
	    viewer. Four mouse clicks and the errors will be
	    highlighted in the log files, and the values of signals at
	    the error will be seen in the source.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Fedora also ships <code>dinotrace-mode</code> for emacs as
	    <package>emacs-dinotrace-mode</package>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
	<term>eqntott</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>eqntott</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    <package>eqntott</package> converts Boolean logic
	    expressions into a truth table that is useful for
	    preparing input to espresso package for logic
	    minimization, converting logic expressions into simpler
	    forms, and for creating truth
	    tables. <package>eqntott</package> is new for Fedora
	    &PRODVER;.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
	<term>expresso-ab</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>expresso-ab</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    New for Fedora &PRODVER;, <package>espresso</package>
	    takes as input a two-level representation of a two-valued
	    (or multiplevalued) Boolean function, and produces a
	    minimal equivalent representation. It is a boolean logic
	    minimization tool.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
	<term>Verilator</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>verilator</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    Verilator is the fastest free Verilog HDL simulator. It
	    compiles synthesizable Verilog, plus some PSL,
	    SystemVerilog and Synthesis assertions into C++ or SystemC
	    code. It is designed for large projects where fast
	    simulation performance is of primary concern, and is
	    especially well suited to create executable models of CPUs
	    for embedded software design teams.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
	<term>vrq</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>vrq</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    VRQ is modular verilog parser that supports plugin tools
	    to process verilog.  Multiple tools may be invoked in a
	    pipeline fashion within a single execution of vrq. It is a
	    generic front-end parser with support for plugin backend
	    customizable tools.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
	<term>Alliance</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Alliance</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <para>
	    Fedora Alliance CVS devel repository got its 100th patch
	    in August 2009, with respect to stability on 64
	    architecture and we are happy that upstream has applied
	    all our patches for alliance. We have also built this new
	    release for all Fedora supported testing repositories and
	    EPEL-5 testing repository. There is also a new GUI
	    <package>xgra</package> coming with this new release which
	    is a Graph viewer.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    We will not replace Alliance VLSI by herb (which was
	    supported to be a fork of alliance) on Fedora. Before
	    F-11’s release, herb development was active but died out
	    after F-11 was released. Since Alliance VLSI upstream is
	    active and responsive to our wishes, there is currently no
	    valid reason behind obsoleting alliance in favour of herb.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Perl Scripts for hardware Design</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>perl-SystemPerl</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm><primary>perl-SystemPerl</primary></indexterm>
	  <para>This is a new package for Fedora &PRODVER;.</para>
	  <para>
	    SystemPerl is a version of the SystemC language. It is
	    designed to expand text so that needless repetition in the
	    language is minimized. By using sp_preproc, SystemPerl files
	    can be expanded into C++ files at compile time, or expanded
	    in place to make them valid stand-alone SystemC files.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>perl-Verilog-Perl</term>
	<listitem>
	  <indexterm><primary>perl-Verilog-Perl</primary></indexterm>
	  <para>
	    <package>perl-Verilog-Perl</package> has been updated to
	    version 3.123.  New features include:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Improved warning when "do" used as identifier.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Fixed escaped preprocessor identifiers, bug106.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Fixed Perl 5.8.8 compile error, rt48226.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Fixed Perl 5.8.0 compile error with callbackgen.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    <warning>
	      <para>
		perl-Verilog-Perl obsoletes perl-Verilog. Fedora users
		are advised to tune their home-made Perl scripts
		accordingly.
	      </para>
	    </warning>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

</section>


