<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<appendix id="appe-Release_Notes-Legal_Information">
	<title>Legal Information</title>
	<para>
		The Fedora Project is sponsored by Red Hat, Inc.
	</para>
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Legal_Information-License">
		<title>License</title>
		<para>
			The Fedora License Agreement is included with each release. A reference version is available on the Fedora Project website: <ulink type="http" url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal/Licenses/LicenseAgreement">http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal/Licenses/LicenseAgreement</ulink> This document is licensed under the terms of the Open Publication License v1.0 without options: <ulink type="http" url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal/Licenses/OPL">http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal/Licenses/OPL</ulink>
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Legal_Information-Trademarks">
		<title>Trademarks</title>
		<para>
			&#39;Fedora&#39; and the Fedora logo are trademarks of Red Hat, Inc. and are subject to the terms of the Fedora Trademark Guidelines: <ulink type="http" url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal/TrademarkGuidelines">http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal/TrademarkGuidelines</ulink> All other trademarks are the property of their respective owners.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Legal_Information-External_References">
		<title>External References</title>
		<para>
			This document may link to other resources that are not under the control of and are not maintained by the Fedora Project. Red Hat, Inc. is not responsible for the content of those resources. We provide these links only as a convenience, and the inclusion of any link to such a resource does not imply endorsement by the Fedora Project or Red Hat of that resource. We reserve the right to terminate any link or linking program at any time.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Legal_Information-Export">
		<title>Export</title>
		<para>
			Certain export restrictions may apply to Fedora Project releases. Refer to <ulink type="http" url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal/Export">http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal/Export</ulink> for more details.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Legal_Information-Legal_Information">
		<title>Legal Information</title>
		<para>
			The following legal information concerns some software in Fedora. Portions Copyright (c) 2002-2007 Charlie Poole or Copyright (c) 2002-2004 James W. Newkirk, Michael C. Two, Alexei A. Vorontsov or Copyright (c) 2000-2002 Philip A. Craig
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Release_Notes-Legal_Information-More_Information">
		<title>More Information</title>
		<para>
			Additional legal information surrounding this document and Fedora Project releases is available on the Fedora Project website: <ulink type="http" url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal       ">http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Legal </ulink>
		</para>
	</section>

</appendix>

